The scene is Athens, 400 BC.
صحنه رو در آتن تجسم کنيد، 400 سال قبل از ميلاد مسيح
A bunch of the local braniacs have gotten together, the wine is being passed,
روهي از بزران محلي دور هم جمع شدند، شراب در حال سرو شدنه
and the ideas are flowing fast and furious. The debate's in full force,
از هر دري صحبت ميشه جمعيت غرق فتو هستند
and Socrates has the floor. Who enters? Alcibíades,
و سقراط مجلس رو توي مشتش داره کي وارد ميشه؟ افلاطون
drunk, a beautiful man, hopelessly in love with his mentor, Socrates.
مست، زيبا، سوخته در آتش استادش سقراط
And, uniquely, in all of these dialogues,
و بطور عجيبي، با وجود همه ي صحبت هايي که داره انجام ميشه
Socrates doesn't get the last word. Alcibíades does. Why?
سقراط کلام آخر رو درک نمي کنه ولي افلاطون مي فهمه، را؟
Because passion, Plato seems to be saying, is essentially and mercilessly human.
براي اينکه هوا و هوس، افلاطون فته، لازمه ي يک انسانه
And the best that we can hope to do is to quell it,
و بهترين کاري که ما در برابرش مي تونيم انجام بديم، سرکوبي اونه
through relentless discipline.
از طريق رياضت کشي
To Socrates, the healthy life is comprised of constant focus by the individual,
براي سقراط، زندي سالم شامل تمرکز دائمي بوسيله ي خود شخص ست
to excise those forces that weaken or... or confuse his
براي رهايي از عواملي که باعث ضعف يا...يا سردرمي
understanding of the world around him.
برداشت اون از دنياي اطرافش مي شوند
He implores us to devote our lives to this kind of control.
اون به ما التماس مي کنه که زنديمون رو به کنترل غرايضمون اختصاص بديم
Meaning, our every waking moment.
در واقع، تک تک لحظه هايي رو که در هوشياري به سر مي بريم
Socrates recognized what every philosopher
سقراط يزي رو فهميد که همه ي فيلسوف ها
and religion, for that matter, in the history of the world,
و مذاهب دنيا
from Plato to Aristotle, from Epicurus to the Stoics,
از افلاطون تا ارسطو از ايکور تا رواقيون (نام فيلسوف يونانى که معتقد بود خوش ذرانى منتهاى سعادت، و خوبى است)
from the Judeo-Christians to the Buddhists, have all observed,
از يهود و مسيحيت تا بودائيسم، همي بهش معتقد بودند
which is that the balance needed for a happy life
و براي يک زندي همراه با خوشبختي، اونو لازم مي دونستند
is illusory.
همه ش توهم بوده ست
And as soon as in our gorgeously-flawed human way
و بزودي اين زندي رزرق و برق امروزي ما
we think that we've attained it.
که فکر مي کنيم مدينه ي فاضله ي ماست
We're pretending divinity, and we're gonna crash,
و ما در اون تظاهر به خدارستي مي کنيم در واقع آرام آرام ما رو به سمت تباهي مي بره
like Icarus, flaming into the sea.
مثل ايکاروس سر دالوس، که با شعله اي در دريا راه مي رفت
So think about that this weekend, when you think you're
س تو تعطيلات آخر هفته روي اين موضوع خوب فکر کنيد وقتي که
on top of the world, and then you pour a pitcher of beer
فکر مي کنين بر قله ي دنيا ايستاديد، در حاليکه آبجويي که توي دستتون دارين رو
down your throat and chase that upper-classman, who's out of your league.
آرام آرام مي نوشيد، و  فکرتون دنبال همکلاسيتونه که از شما خيلي سرتره
Aristotle is next week. Don't just look at it as words.
ارسطو بمونه براي جلسه ي بعد به شم درس حفظ کردني به مطالب ناه نکنين
Imagine the scene. These were people. They were alive, like you and me.
تخيلتون رو بکار بندازيد، اينا هم انسان بودند مثل من و شما زندي مي کردند
They thought these things. Breathe 'em into life.
اينا افکار اوناست زنده شون کنين
So, I was thinking about doing a sort of contrast
بنابراين، من به فکر يه جور تقابل افتادم
between dialogue and chorus in Sophocles.
بين ديالو ها و سرايندان
Now you should check out Nietzsche's Birth of Tragedy.
بهتره که کتاب تولد تراژدي نيه رو هم يک ورقي بزني
He says that tragedy emerges from the clash between Apollo,
اون ميه که تراژدي از برخورد آولو
god of reason and harmony, and Dionysus, god of intoxication.
خداي دليل و برهان و ديونسيس، خداي شراب و ميساري بوجود مي ياد
And that their struggle within our human condition is inevitable, and
و تأثير نبرد اون ها در دايره ي زندي ما اجتناب ناذيره
that is what has produced the most salient form of art the world's ever known.
و دليل انواع مختلف هنرهايي که امروزه در دنيا مي بينيم، همينه
- Tragedy? - What, you don't think so?
- تراژدي؟ - نظر ديه اي داري؟
I like comedies. 'Ya wanna see a movie?
کمدي رو بيشتر مي سندم، دوست داري يه فيلمي ببينيم؟
No, Miss Greenstein, I'm sorry.
نه، دوشيزه رينستاين، متأسفم
- Did you get my note? - I did. - And?
- يادداشتم دستتون رسيد؟ - بله - خب؟
It was very clever of you to write it in Latin.
خيلي هوشمندانه بود که به لاتين نوشته بودي
With the repeated use of the passive periphrastic?
با تکرار الفاظ زائد انفعالي؟
- It was quite propagate. - And how I was sending up Cicero
- زياده روي کرده بودي
with all those alliterative adjectives thrusting themselves into the verbs?
حتي با وجود اون همه تلاشي که براي بکار بردن صفاتي کردم که مي تونستند به فعل تبديل شوند؟
- None of this was lost on me. - So?
-  هي کدومشون بر من وشيده نبود - خب؟
Miss Greenstein,
دوشيزه رينستاين
you are very, very bright and very profession in your way,
شما خيلي خيلي با استعداد هستين و آينده ي درخشاني هم داريد
But there are certain rules, mores (mawr-eyz), if you will,
ولي حد و مرزهايي هست رسومي هست
lines that we don't cross.
خطوطي که نميتونيم از اونا عبور کنيم
I'm not joking, actually, and I'm gonna ask you in the future to refrain...
...شوخي نمي کنم، در واقع ازتون مي خوام که مانع
No! No, no, no... No! Please, don't do that!
!نه! نه، نه،نه،...نه اين کار رو با من نکنيد
I'm gonna ask you to open that door, Miss Greenstein.
تقاضا دارم اون درب رو باز کنيد
Lingua sed torpet, tenuis sub artus [But my tongue becomes immobile]
(زبان من خشک شده ست" (به لاتين ميه"
Flamma demanat, sonitu suopte [A thin flame goes down under my weak limbs]
"آتشي در وجود من شعله ور شده ست"
Catullus 51, the Lesbia cycle, yes. However,
Catullus شعر شماره ي 51
Oh, no, no, no! Abs... Absolutely not!
!اوه، نه، نه ،نه عمرا
Miss Greenstein!
دوشيزه رينستاين
This is not good for either of us!
اين در شأن ما دو نفر نيست
No, Miss Greenstein! No! Restrain yourself!
!نه! دوشيزه رينستاين، نه حد خودتون رو نه دارين
Oh! Oh! Excuse me! Um... I... I... I...
!اوه! اوه! بب....ببخشيد! من! من!...من
Maggie! Mag... Maggie! Please don't go. Miss Greenstein was just leaving.
!مي! م م م...مي دوشيزه رينستاين تشريف مي بردند
- Maggie. Absolutely nothing. - You don't have to say anything.
- مي، مطلقا هي خبري نبود - احتياجي نيست يزي بيد
I would never... She... She... She went and just puh!
!من هيوقت...اون اون اون يهو ريد روي من
They're all in love with you. Just like Harvard.
همه عاشق شما هستن مثل زمان هاروارد
Who told you that?
کي اينو بهت فته؟
This is the classics department. No one is more gossipy than you people.
اينجا يه دارتمان سنتيه، دوروبر افرادي مثل شما هميشه شايعه موج ميزنه
Ok, I am going to Cambridge in the morning. It's just a lunch.
باشه، من صبح ميرم به کمبريج، فقط يه ضيافته
I don't wanna know.
نمي خوام بدونم
We don't deal in crystal meth. We don't deal in cocaine.
ما شيشه رد نمي کنيم ما کوکائين رد نمي کنيم
Not your rock stuff or your powder.
جنس آشغالي تو کارمون نيست
We don't do nothing ya gotta cook up in a spoon and shoot into your arm.
يزي رو نمياريم که بريزيش توي قاشقتو !و آبش کني و بفرستيش توي ر بي صاحابت
Pills? Pharmaceuticals? Hell, no, by and large.
قرص؟ دوا؟ عمرا
Maybe, well, maybe the black molly's gonna pass through these hands
حالا شايد، شايد ماهي دودي با اين دستا جا به جا شده باشه
on his way to somewheres else, just on account of the fact I used to like
که اونم فقط يه جا رفته به جون ننه ام
pop in high school, 'cuz I had to get my homework done.
صاف رفته به آشزخونه ي دبيرستان
But that's generally where we draw the line.
قلمرو کاري عمدتا همون وراست
No, sir. We deal in 100% pure Oklahoma grown, exclusive. Why?
نه قربان، ما جنسمون صد در صد خالص، مي رسي را؟
Because I ain't gonna blow my house up mixing up antihistamines into dynamite.
ون دوس نداريم خونمون رو سر قاطي کردن آنتي هيستامين با ديناميت بفرستيم هوا
And, spiritually, I don't cotton to somethin'
و به جون ننه م يزي رو لاوشوني نکردم
that's gotta pass through a needle.
که بخوام از شما نهونش کنم
Chemicals, well, I just don't like 'em.
جنس شميايي؟ من شيميم هميشه ضعيف بوده
My people was bootleggers before all this.
فک و فاميل ما هميشه تو کار غير قانوني بودن
It was a backyard operation. They did it natural.
يه جايي اون شت مشتا داشتن طبيعي کار مي کردن
Little bit more of a science nowadays. I will grant ya that.
از جنساي امروزي باکلاس تر بودن تضمين مي کنم به جون ننه م
You say you changed your mind, getcha up north.
اه نظرت عوض شده بهتره بري شمال که نبينيمت
- He mentioned Texas. - Texas ain't gonna happen.
- منظورش تزاسه - تزاس به درد نمي خوره
Dick, we don't wanna sell in Texas.
ديک، ما که نمي خوايم تو تزاس فروش داشته باشيم
Kansas, Nebraska, Missouri.
کانزاس، نبرسکا، ميسوري
I ain't interested.
باهاشون حال نمي کنم
He say you'd better get your mind around being interested.
اونم منظورش همينه، مي خواد که يه جوري باهاش حال کني
Meaning what?
منظور؟
Meaning your choice is to expand your business, or we shut you down entire.
منظور اينکه يا بساطتو اونور ميکشوني، يا جدولت رو حل مي کنيم
Then how you gonna pay your debt?
اونوقت ه جوري مي خواي قرضاتو بدي؟
- Well, what happened to Fat Back? - Arrested last week.
- راستي، باک خيکي ي شد؟ - هفته يش رفتنش
- And the Rawls feller up in Liberty Mans? - Blowed his house up.
- رالس ي شد؟ - خونه خراب شد
Oh, see, that's.. that what I'm talkin' about.
بيا، منم دارم همين رو مي م
Well, it's tough times.
خب، زمونه ي سختي شده
Well, ain't it the truth.
اينو قبول ندارم
Used to be, you could get a couple of trip wires, a couple of booby traps,
قبلا شما با يه مشت سيم، ند تا آژير
a good set of dogs, you pay off your local constable,
يه دسته س مهربون طرف بودين حق حساب افسر محلتون رو سر وقت مي دادين
and you just live out on the property.
و يزايي که يرتون ميومد رو مي تونستين نير دارين
Feed her a little 13-13-13 fertilizer, like growing summer beans.
کافيه يکم مثل لوبيايي که تابستونا ميکارن، بهش کود بدين
Even the war on drugs passed us by.
راحت مشکل جن سر نرخ دواتون هم تموم ميشه
Course, now they come up with the war on terror.
معلومه، اين روزا دعوا سر نرخ آدمکشيه
Not that I ain't interested in the travails of a small-time drug dealer,
ولش اونقدري نيست که زحمت ساقي هاي نجيشک روزي ناديده رفته بشه
- Oh, you calling me small-time? - We gotta make it to Tulsa.
- به من ميي نجيشک روزي؟ - برناممون براي محله ي تولساست
Do you know that I was the first grower in the State that ever employed hydroponics?
مي دونستي من اولين نفري توي اين ولايت بودم که روش غرقابي رو جور کردم؟
What's hydroponics?
غرقابي ه کوفتيه؟
Germinating the seed in water, you shit-for-brains.
يعني جوونه ش رو توي آب ميزارن، خنول
Do you know how many generations of hybridization
ميدوني قدر قلمه زني اين روزا
I've had to do to get my top three varietals?
بايد انجام بدم که بتونم سه تا جنس توم رو آماده کنم؟
There is a goddamn reason I grow the best!
براي همين خرحمالي هاست که الان بهترين رورش دهنده منم
- Enough, Brady. What's it gonna be? - Pug wants his money!
- کافيه، برادي. آخرش که ي؟ - ا ولشو مي خواد
Well, If I'd a known about a timetable, we'd have been doing that.
خب، اه بهم بين تا کي وقت دارم مي تونم يه کاريش بکنم
Shut your face about a timetable. He's offering you a way out.
خفه خون بير اون مي خواد که روشت رو عوض کني
You sure as shit better take it,
خودتم مي دوني که بهتره قبول کني
or he's gonna bust up in your glory hole, like nobody's business.
ورنه بساطتو به هم مي ريزه
We should turn it loose.
بايد اين خوشلک ها رو تکون بديم
I ain't gonna manufacture or purvey
من جنس مصنوعي تو کارم نيست
anything that I won't ingest into my own sweet self. Lookit here.
هريزي که دوست نداشته باشم خودم بخورم اينو ببين
How you gonna call that a controlled substance?
ه جوري ميشه اينو يه جنس دست ين حساب کرد(ملاک سنجشت يه)؟
- Well, the government do. - Look at the bud structure on it.
- خب، دولت که حساب ميکنه - جوونه ي روي اين رو ببين
The crystal density, the smell of them terpenes. You can't synthesize that.
کريستال متراکم شده روش، بوي تِرن هاش عمرا بتوني مصنوعي بسازيش
That is nature's delivery system for goodness,
سيستم دقيق طبيعت روش کار کرده
distilled into a pure form.
و اونو تبديل به يه جنس خالص کرده
It glides down into your belly, and blooms into a feeling of peace,
اين سُر مي خوره و تا شکمت ائين ميره و يه حس آرامشي داخلت رديف ميکنه
in this world beset by evil.
باهاش شيطونم نمي تونه دنيا رو داغون کنه
That world is gonna be there, no matter how much grass you smoke.
اين دنيا داغون هست، حالا هرقدر مي خواي علف بکش
Now, look here. You wanted to build the fucking Taj Mahal to hydroponics.
حالا ببينم، مي خواي يه يزي مثل تاج محل براي اين غرقابي هات بسازي؟
- Well? - And you done it.
- خب؟ - خب ساختي
But you know what you was gettin' into with him,
اما ميدوني يش طرف زونده
and he sure as shit ain't goin' away.
و حالا فهميده اوضاعش ند شده
Brady!
برادي
My mind's workin' on it.
همه ي فکرم روي اين قضيه ست
Well, I sat down in the closet, with all my overalls
Well, I sat down in the closet, with all my overalls
Tryin' to get away from all the ears inside my walls
Tryin' to get away from all the ears inside my walls
Dreamed the police heard everything I thought... what then?
Dreamed the police heard everything I thought... what then?
Well, I went to court and the judge's name was Hoffman
Well, I went to court and the judge's name was Hoffman
- Howdy, Sharon. Where's she at? - Oh, she's in her usual spot.
- هاودي، شارون. کجاست؟ - همون جا هميشيشه
- Hi, Joe! - Brady.
- سلام، جوي - برادي
...to escape reality
...to escape reality
And you may see me tonight, with an illegal smile
And you may see me tonight, with an illegal smile
It don't cost very much...
It don't cost very much...
- Hey, mama. - Oh, hey. Whatcha got there?
- سلام، مامان - سلام، ي دستته؟
Oh... It's a new article on Billy, and a theory he wrote hisself.
اوه، اين مقاله ي جديد بيليه و تئوريه که خودش داده
Thank you.
مرسي
- Ya know, I've been thinkin'. - Hmm?
- ميدوني، داشتم فکر مي کردم - خب؟
Maybe, maybe your daddy wanted to get killed.
شايد، شايد بابات خودش دوست داشت بميره
Somehow, I got this picture of him, runnin' toward a machine gun,
بعضي وقتها، خيالشو مي کنم که مي بينمش که به سمت لوله ي تفن مي دوه
because he'd rather die that way,
ون، خودش اينجور مردن رو ترجيح مي داد
than come back to Little Dixie, and grow old, stare through a window.
تا بررده اينجا و ير بشه و زل بزنه به نجره
Well, seeing how he was on about every drug imaginable,
خب، وقتي مي ديدم که به هر دارويي متوسل ميشه
I... I wouldn't spend my time trying to figure out
نمي خوام وقتمو سر فکر کردن به اين بذارم
what was in his head over 30 years ago.
که ي از 30 سال يش توي سرش مونده بود
Do you remember him at all?
اونو کامل يادت مونده؟
I remember smelling weed the first time... on him.
يادمه بوي حشيش رو اول...از اون شنيدم
Well, that certainly had its impact.
خب، آخرش هم لطمه شو بهش زد
Daisy, why... why don't you come home with us
ديزي، را نمياي خونه با ما باشي؟
and live with me and Colleen for awhile?
و يه مدتي با من و کالين سر کني؟
- Colleen and me.
- کالين و من
What's your version of proper grammar?
طرز اداي کلمات تو ه مدليه؟
Rhythm, maybe. Dumb Dutch question.
آهنين، شايدم سبک احمقانه ي فرانسوي
You're 12 years younger than anyone in here. This is ridiculous!
تو از بقيه 12 سال کويکتري، اين خيلي احمقانه ست (مادرش توي خونه ي سالمندانه)
I like it here. I can do what I want,
اينجا بودن رو دوست دارم، اينجا هرکاري بخوام مي تونم بکنم
and I'm not eager to get stranded when you get yourself killed or taken back to prison.
و نمي خوام وقتي انداختنت زندان، لن بمونم
Mama, Colleen is pregnant.
مامان، کالين حامله ست
You don't say?
س را حرفي نمي زني؟
I've been dying to tell 'ya!
داشتم مي مردم بهت بم
Ahhh, well, I'm happy for you.
وااااي، قدر برات ذوق کردم
Well, how 'bout you? You're gonna be a grandma.
براي خودتم بکن، ناسلامتي داري مامان بزر ميشي
Are you gonna be a husband?
مي خواي از امروز براش شوهري کني؟
I ain't dead.
نمردم که
Your father was a freaked-out genius who wasted his life.
بابات يه نابغه ي ترسويي بود که زنديش رو به ند کشيد
He could have done anything.
اون همه کار مي تونست بکنه
Got a higher IQ than your brother, and he just passed you by.
تو مغزت از داداشت بيشتر کار مي کرد ولي عقب موندي
I... I... I ain't tryin' to keep up with Billy.
من...من...من نمي تونم مثل بيلي تلاش کنم
I ain't him, and he ain't me.
من اون نيستم، اونم من نيست
Mama, I like who I am just fine.
مامان، من همين جوريش راضيم
You think I'll see him again before I die?
فکر مي کني قبل از مردن بتونم باز هم ببينمش؟
I think it's gonna take one of us dying to get him to come back down here.
فکر کنم يکيمون بايد بميره تا ايشون قدم رنجه کنند اينجا بيان
Well, nice sittin' with ya.
خب، خوش ذشت
Gorgeous.
زيباست
This is wonderful. I... I... I almost never eat out in Providence.
اين فوق العاده ست من...من...من...هي وقت اينجا غذا نخورده بودم
I hear your book on Marcus Aurelius has the whole community astir.
شنيدم کتابت در مورد مارکوس آئرليوس با اقبال عمومي مواجه شده
- Oh, thanks. - Which press was that again? -Oxford.
- اوه، ممنونم - توي کدام نشريه بود؟ - آکسفورد
But they did your translation of the Menaechmi last year.
ارسال هم يه ترجمه ي لاتين از تو ذاشته بودند
They did. They've been terrific.
بله، کارشون عاليه
Plautus. How do you find the time?
حيرت انيزه. ه جوري وقت براي اين کارا ير مياري؟
Well, I don't have a life.
خب، من کار ديه اي تو زنديم ندارم
I read some biographical material on you last week, Bill.
من ند تا مطلب در مورد تو هفته يش خوندم
You, ah, you come from humble beginnings.
تو از محله ي ستي شروع کردي
I do, yea.
بله
- Where was it? Omaha? - Oklahoma.
- کجا بود؟ اوماها؟ - اُکلوهاما
Oh, why don't you, ah, why don't you have an accent?
س را...س را لهجه نداري؟
With some considerable effort, I lost it.
با کلي تمرين، از دست دادمش
- Your father was a bootlegger. - It was my grandfather, actually.
- درت توي کار خلاف بود - در حقيقت، دربزرم توي کار خلاف بود
- Fantastic. - Why fantastic?
- جالبه - را؟
I don't know. So many of us were trained for this life.
نمي دونم، خيلي از ماها براي اين زندي آموزش ديديم (يعني خونواده هامون آدم حسابي بودند)
Fancy private schools, parents in academia.
توي مدرسه خصوصي درس خونديم خونواده هامون تحصيلات آکادميک داشتند
I'm always astounded by those who made their own way.
من هميشه اونايي که روي اي خودشون مي ايستند رو ستايش مي کنم
Oh, thank you. I, ah, my family is a bit eccentric.
متشکرم، فکر کنم خانواده ام کمي عجيب بودند
I found discipline in books.
من انظباط رو توي کتاب ها يدا کردم
Well, you're probably wondering why Dean Sorenson is here.
حتما تعجب کردي را دَن سورنسن هم اينجاست
Bill, we'd like to offer you a position in the Law School.
بيل، مايليم که کرسي تدريس توي مدرسه حقوق را بهت يشنهاد بديم
You can't be serious?
شوخي مي کنين؟
We've been wanting to incorporate more philosophy into the curriculum,
ما مي خوايم فلسفه رو بصورت جدي تري وارد برنامه ي آموزشيمون کنيم
and when we got wind of your hesitancy in transferring up from Brown in Classics,
و وقتي آوازه ي تو رو شنيديم
we came up with the idea of letting you create
خواستيم که با کمک تو اينکار انجام بشه
your own institute for our law students.
نهادي به اسم تو براي دانش آموزان ما
I, ah, don't even know how to begin to respond. That is such a precipitous offer.
نمي دونم ي بم يشنهاد غافليرکننده اي بود
Savor it. Digest it.
حسش کن هضمش کن
Moments like this come too seldom in life.
اين جور شانس ها کم در خونه ي آدم رو ميزنه
I, ah, I'll say.
راست ميي
We all want you here, Bill. You've crafted your career diligently.
هر ي مي خواي مهياست آينده ت تضمين ميشه
It makes absolute sense as your next step.
اين دقيقا قدم بعدي تو توي مسير يشرفتته
You've a dollop of japeno.
!زير لبت رو کثيف کردي
Mmm, honey, that's better, you're the best.
عزيزم، بهتر شده کارت حرف نداره
Thank you, Brady.
مرسي، برادي
- Look how sexy you look. - I do not. - You do.
- ه خوشل شدي امشب - نه بابا - را بابا
How long the doctor give me till I got to throw up that old detour sign?
دکتر قدري وقت براي به حساب کرده؟
Well, just wait till I'm done with these dishes.
خب، بزار اول کار ظرفها رو تموم کنم
Oh, well, push that... Gonna put you right on the burner. Bring it, electric!
خب، حالا يه زوري بزن...مي خواي بزارمت روي اجاق !تا به زودتر عمل بياد
Hello?
الو؟
Well, can I ask who's calling?
بله، شما؟
Can I ask what this is about?
در موردِ؟
Because I'm the girlfriend he's fixin' to marry, is why.
ون که بنده دوست دختري هستم که قراره باهاش ازدواج کنن
- Who is it? Who is it? - Some fellow named Pug.
- کيه؟ کيه؟ - يه بابايي به اسم ا
- I'll take it in the back there. - It better not be...
- بدش به من - ...بهتره که
It ain't, it ain't. It's a man about a truck.
نيست، نيست براي کاميون زن زده
Hey, Brady!
هي، برادي
- Hey, Pug. How are y... - [indistinct] down there, Brady?
- ...سلام ا، طوري - به ها رو ديدي برادي؟
- Ooh, oh, ah, yes we did. - They told you I needed an answer?
- !اوه، اوه، اوه بله - بهت فتن منتظر جوابم؟
Yes, sir, they made that pretty clear. I was just hopin'...
بله کاملا واضح و روشن ...من فقط اميدوار
I want to see you tomorrow evening.
مي خوام فردا غروب ببينمت
- Well, tomorrow night's gonna be... - You heard me, Brady!
- ...خب، فردا شب - شنيدي که ي فتم
- Yea? - Bolger! - Hey, buddy. - Pug just called me.
- بله - بالر؟ - سلام برادي - ا الان زن زد
Pug called you hisself?
ا خودش بهت زن زد؟
Yea, he want us up there.
آره، کارمون داره
- What does he want? - No, he want to see us.
- نفت ي؟ - نه، مي خواد ببينتمون
- You gonna change...? - No, I ain't changin' my mind one bit.
- ...مي خواي که - نه، نظرم يه ذره هم عوض نشده
- I don't like this at all, Brady. - Well, we just gonna have to
- از اين اوضاع خوشم نمياد برادي - ...مجبوريم که
be ready to deal then and come what may.
آماده ي هر اتفاقي باشيم...
You know me, I'm gonna be up there with ya.
مي دوني که منم باهات ميام
I'll see ya.
مي بينمت
Hello?
بله؟
Lola who?
لولا ي؟
Ah, ah, ah, hang on, hang on.
صبر کن، صبر کن
How did you get this number?
ه جوري اين شماره رو ير آوردي؟
Hi, did that man get a hold of you?
سلام، اون مرد تونست با شما تماس بيره؟
He did, yea.
بله
He said it was an emergency, so I...
فتش اضطراريه ...منم مجبور شدم
You did the right thing, thanks.
کار درستي کردي، ممنونم
Was there something else?
يز ديه اي هم هست؟
Is everything all right?
همه يز رو به راهه؟
Well, my brother's been murdered.
برادرم بقتل رسيده
Bill, that's awful!
بيل، اين وحشتناکه
I didn't even know you had a brother!
نمي دونستم برادري هم داري
How?
طور اين اتفاق افتاده؟
He got shot with a crossbow.
با کمان زنبوري (صليبي) تير خورده
I beg your pardon?
ببخشيد؟
They're inexplicably popular where I come from.
اونجايي که من ازش اومدم اينجور وسايل معموليه
Was it an accident?
اتفاقي بوده؟
No, because then it wouldn't be a murder.
نه، اه بود که قتل زارش نمي شده
Ah, oh, I don't know even know what... When was the last time you saw him?
...اوه، من نمي دونم ي بايد ب آخرين بار کي ديده بوديش؟
Um, it had been a long time.
خيلي وقت يش
What will you do?
حالا کار مي کني؟
Well, ah, I suppose I have to go home.
فکر کنم بايد برردم خونه
What brings you to Tulsa?
ي شما را به تولسا کشونده؟
Pardon? Oh, ah, family matter.
ببخشيد؟ اوه يه مشکل خانوادي
I was gonna say, because nobody visits Oklahoma, ya know,
براي اين فتم که، ميدوني، کسي معمولا براي ديدن اُکلوهاما همين جوري نمياد
and it's one of those states where you live there, maybe you got business there,
و اين از اون ايالت هايي هست که شايد ...به درد زندي يا کار بخوره
but you don't see people coming for the attractions.
اما توريستي نيست...
- Right. - What do ya do?
- درسته - شغلتون يه؟
I, ah, I write and teach. I'm a professor.
من، مي نويسم و درس مي دهم من يک استاد دانشاهم
- Of? - Classical Philosophy.
- استاده؟ - فلسفه ي باستاني
There's not too much use for that these days.
اين روزا کاربرد نداني نداره، نه؟
Humanity hasn't changed that much, actually.
انسانيت که عوض نشده
Do you have family in Tulsa?
خانواده اي هم در تولسا داري؟
No, no. Idabel.
نه، نه در آيدابِل دارم
Little Dixie?
ديکسيِ کوک؟
I hope it's not tragedy that brings you back.
اميدوارم غم تو رو به اينجا نکشونده باشه
- It is for someone. - I'm sorry. - Thanks
- اندوهِ کس ديه ايه - متأسفم - ممنونم
I'm an orthodontist.
من اورتودنتيست هستم
Was, I mean. Will be again.
بودم، در واقع دوباره شروع کردم
Have you had work done?
دندونات رو به راهه؟
- No, no, actually, I haven't. - Yea, I can.. I can tell.
- نه، نه در واقع نيست - آره، مي بينم
You got a nice face, though.
هره ي مناسبي داري
Thanks.
ممنون
- Ken Feinman - Bill Kincaid
- کين فِين مَن - بيل کين کِيد
- You have kids, Bill? - No
- به هم داري؟ - نه
I'm starting out all over. Yea.
من دوباره از صفر شروع کردم
People don't realize it, but it's... it's tough to break in, and you get
...مردم درک نمي کنند، ولي سخته که بعد از يک شکست دوباره شروع کني
most of your business, ya know, through your kids' school, in your church,
بيشتر دل مشغوليت اين روزا، صرف تحصيل به هات توي مدرسه ...و يا آموزش هاي مذهبيشون در کليسا و يا
synagogue, in my case, ya know,
کنيسه (براي يهوديان)، درمورد من، ميشه...
but it's tough, I mean the costs of a practice these days
ولي زور داره، مي دوني هزينه ي تحصيل اين روزا کمرشکنه
Honestly, it's
واقعا ناجوانمردانه ست
- Hmm, yea, I believe you. - We were living in Manhattan,
- راست ميي - ما توي منهتن زندي مي کنيم
but, ah, I grew up in Tulsa, so, ya know, we just moved back.
ولي، من توي تولسا متولد شدم الان هم مي دوني، حالا هم دارم بر مي ردم
Are there a lot of Jews in Tulsa?
يهودي هاي تولسا زيادند؟
That's.. that's what.. that's what everyone asks,
...اين...اين رو اين يزيه که همه مي رسند
but.. but there are. No, it's...
....ولي اونجا...، نه اونجا
it's a small community, but very cohesive,
جامعه ي کويکي ازشون هست ولي بسيار متحدند
and, ya know, the pull was unimaginable.
و، مي دوني، جاذبه عجيبي دارند
Kenny, do you see the man is reading?
کِني، نمي بيني آقا داشتند مطالعه مي کردند؟
I don't think he wants to sit and listen to you
فکر نکنم علاقه اي به شنيدن صحبت هاي تو داشته باشند
chronicle the evolution of Tulsa Jewry.
!تاريخه ي تکامل يهوديان تولسا
I'll let you get back to your reading.
مطالعتون رو بکنيد
Thanks.
ممنونم
It's a little embarrassing. I don't.. don't mean to be..
شرمنده ام ...نمي خوام...نمي خوام که
It's just, ah, if you've got family down there.
فقط، اه اينجا خويشاوندي داري
- Ya know, nieces and nephews... - I don't.
- ...مي دوني، برادرزاده يا خواهرزاده اي که - ندارم
I mean, if you did or, you know...
...حالا اه موردي بود، ممکنه
It's, ah, it's.. it's not too far away,
مي دوني...خيلي از اينجا دور نيست
- and, ah, you know, I do great work. - I.. I know you do.
- من هم کارم خوبه - مي دونم
I never take accidental encounters for granted.
من هي بورس يا کمک دولتي دريافت نکردم
- Kenny! Kenny! - So... I'm gonna run.
- !کِني! کِني - خب...بايد عجله کنم
- Rick Bolger - Hey, Rick.
- ريک بالر - سلام، ريک
-Folks call me Bolger. - Nice to meet ya.
-رفقا منو بالر صدا مي کنند - خوشوقتم
Man! You sure do look like him.
!سر! تو کُِ داداشتي
I think that's what they mean by identical.
فکر کنم همساني که مين يعني همين
Your brother was a great friend to me.
داداشت دوست خوبي براي من بود
I... I hadn't seen him in awhile, but.. thanks.
من...من مدت زيادي ميشه که نديدمش، ولي ممنونم
- You ain't got no bags? - No, that's it.
- بند و بساطي همراهت نيست؟ - نخير
Nice to meet you.
خوشوقتم قربان
My wildest dreams grow wilder every day
My wildest dreams grow wilder every day
There's nothing I can think or do or say
There's nothing I can think or do or say
I ain't been up here in awhile. I was gonna stay in a hotel.
من زياد اينجا نمي مونم مي رم به هتلم
Where'd ya go?
کجا هست؟
Found me a dead-end in a construction site near the airport.
منو توي يه ساختمون نيمه کاره کنار فروداه ميتوني يدا کني
Laid out, counting stars. Crazy how much building they got goin' on up there.
دراز کشيده، در حال شمارش ستاره ها، در شفت از اينکه ند تا ساختمون مي خوان اون بيرون بسازند
Folks just don't take to the country no more, I guess.
رفقا، ديه اين اطراف يداشون نميشه
You figure?
رفتي مطلبو؟
Mystery...
...عجيبه
I swear I'll get it right
I swear I'll get it right
My wildest dreams grow wilder every day
My wildest dreams grow wilder every day
I'm wonderin' just how far my mind can stray
I'm wonderin' just how far my mind can stray
Just how wild is too high a price to pay
Just how wild is too high a price to pay
You need a drink or anything?
نوشيدني نمي خواي؟
Comin' up on Broken Bow. Can stop off at the Me Tote Em.
بريم کافه و يه يزي بزنيم
Sure.
بريم
Me Tote?
!!کافه؟
Oh! I almost forgot. This here is your brother's.
اوه داشت يادم مي رفت اين مال داداشت بود
I don't know if you want it.
نمي دونستم که مي خوايش يا نه
You're shittin' me.
!به حق يزاي نديده
Buddy!
بادي
You clean up nice.
رو به راه شدي
How's that?
ي؟
Where's the tux from?
لباسا از کجا رسيده؟
Oh, God, no, no, wait a second, wait a second. You, you...
...آه، خدايا، يه دقيقه صبر کن
- Where's Bolger at? - He's around back, but I'm... I'm not who you think I am.
- بالر کجا رفت؟ - همين اطرافه، ببين اوني که فکر مي کني من نيستم
- Oh, you're not? - No, you don't know me.
- نيستي؟ - نه اشتباه رفتي
Oh, well, what I wanna know is what you're doin' up here in Broken Bow,
...يزي که مي خوام بدونم اينه که اينجا کار مي کني
when we don't want you in Broken Bow?
وقتي کسي نمي خواد اينجا باشي؟
Um, it's my mistake. I'm... I'm just gonna leave.
ببخشيد، من...من داشتم مي رفتم
Yea, well, not till Buddy gets here, you won't.
آره، اما تا وقتي که بادي بياد اينجا شما هم تشريف داريد
Buddy?
بادي؟
Calm down! Calm down!
!آروم! آروم
- Keep it up, Brady. - I'm his brother! I'm not... Ohhhh! Ohhhh!
- مسخره بازي بسه برادي - من داداششم، من...اوه ه ه ه
You don't wanna be comin' up north, where you ain't got no tripwires,
تو که فتي نمي خواي بياي شمال ...جايي که از سيم خاردار و
or booby traps, and hos you done bribed.
و آژير و رشوه خبري نيست...
Maybe even sell your souped-up turbo grass to whoever you... [Gunshot]
...حالا اومدي اينجا حشيش هاي مخصوصت رو به هر ننه قمري
- I wondered where you was at. - Don't seem like too fair a fight.
- مونده بودم تو توي کدوم وري قايم شدي - (به نظر عادلانه نمياد (دو نفر به يکي
Well, nobody asked you two to come up north, neither.
کسي هم شما را اينجا دعوت نکرده بود
Well, we had some business to take care of up in Tulsa.
يه سري کار شخصي اين اطراف داشتيم
- I heard somethin' about that. - What you heard?
- در مورد کاراتون يه يزايي به وشم رسيده - ي شنيدي؟
Heard that Brady here owes Pug a lot of money.
شنيدم که برادي يه ول قلمبه اي به ا بدهکاره
Will you explain this, please.
بابا بهشون قضيه رو بو
The less you say to these two fuckin' inbreds, the better.
هري اين دو تا دلقک کمتر بدونن برامون بهتره
Heard he thinks you're gonna expand business down to our Little Dixie.
شنيديم که جنابعالي برنامه يدي که بساطتو تا ديکسي سترش بدي
- The young pussy already said. - How 'bout I say THIS!
- اون رفيق اوشولت اينو قبلا فت - طوره منم اينو بم
How ya feelin'?
طوري؟
- Brady? - Hey, buddy.
- برادي؟ - سلام بادي
What the hell is goin' on?
معلومه ه خبره؟
Well, I think Sally got razor happy.
ديو و دلبر به هم رسيدن
- What? Are you out of your mind? - Okay, easy now.
- ي؟ مخت تکون خورده؟ - خيلي خب، آروم باش
Hold on to him, now. Hold on.
نيرش دار که بدجوري داغ کرده
- No, let go of me! Let me go! - Not until you calm down, he won't!
- !نه ولم کن! ولم کن - تا وقتي آروم نشي، نمي کنه
You had him tell me you were dead? With a fucking crossbow?
تو بهش فتي که خبر مرت رو به من بده؟ با اون قصه ي کمان زنبوري لعنتي؟
Well, all right, I'm sorry 'bout that,
آره، ببخشيد داداشي
but there were no other way for me to get you to come down here.
ولي غير از اين راه نمي تونستم تو رو اينجا بکشونم
Ow! Ow! Ahhh... Down here for what?
!اوه!اوه بکشوني اينجا که ي بشه؟
- I'm gettin' married. - As if I care. What kind of excuse is that?
- دارم زن مي يرم - بير، ه دَخلي به من داره؟
And I'm having a baby. You're gonna be an uncle.
دارم به دار ميشم !تو هم عمو ميشي
Who... Who would be dumb enough to have a child with you?
ببينيم کي...کي اونقدر احمقه که از تو به دار بشه؟
I would.
بنده
You remember the Dentons? On Luminus back home?
دِنتِن ها رو يادت هست؟
- Colleen Denton? - You remember.
- کالين دِنتِن - س يادته
I babysat you when we were in high school.
وقتي دبيرستان مي رفتيم من رستار سرکار خانم بودم
You was my favorite. You used to sit in the kitchen reading books.
من عاشق تو بودم عادت داشتي توي آشزخونه بشيني کتاب بخوني
I got to watch all the TV I wanted, as long as I kept the door shut.
منم تا زماني که در رو مي بستم و سروصدا نمي کردم اجازه داشتم تلويزيون ببينم
You were reading Shakespeare sonnets when I was going to sleep.
وقتي مي خواستم بخوابم برام شکسير مي خوندي
And now you're gonna marry this pothead?
و حالا مي خواي با اين کله کدو ازدواج کني؟
- No, he's not no more. - Ah, leaving all that behind.
- نه، ديه کله کدو نيست - ديه اون دوران تموم شد
Oh, oh, yea, I can see the evidence for that everywhere.
بله بله، نشونه هاش هم همه جا ريخته
I get to keep on smokin' till my baby comes, and then it's cold turkey on that, too.
فقط تا وقتي به به دنيا بياد مي کشم بعد از اون شما روي اين ميز فقط مرغ خته شده مي بينين
But me and Bolger's gonna smoke till the bottom drops out, ain't we?
ولي منو بالر اجازه داريم تا توولي بياد خودمون رو خفه کنيم، نه؟
Oh, what a... what a great time.
!آه، عجب...عجب خوشبختي
Anyway, you know what? I wanna leave as quickly and painlessly as possible.
به هر حال، ميدوني يه؟ مي خوام که از سريعترين و کم دردترين راه ممکنه، بزنم به اک
- Hang on. Just stay through the weekend. - No. - You could go see mom.
- بمون، فقط تا آخر اين هفته بمون - عمرا - مي توني بري مامانو ببيني
Look, Brady, I am leaving. What... What you did here is cruel and irresponsible
ببين برادي، من مي خوام برم کار...کاري که تو کردي خيلي ناجوانمردانه بود
and exactly why I stay away.
و اين همون يزيه که منو از تو جدا مي کنه
No. You... You know I read every goddamn article you write.
نه، تو...تو مي دوني هر رندي که مي نويسي رو من ميخونم؟
I read 50 pages on the interpretation of one word in Aristol.
رو خوندم؟ Aristol مي دوني 50 صفحه تفسير سرکار روي کلمه
Sat there the whole fucking day with a dictionary,
تمام روز رو با يه ديکشنري توي بغلم اينجا نشسته بودم
and not the Merriam Webster, either, the motherfucking OED.
و هي کدوم از اون ديکشنري هات کمکي نکردند
Ain't 20 people in the world read that whole piece, I'll bet,
شرط مي بندم 20 نفر هم توي دنيا مقاله ات رو کامل نخونده باشند
and you're lookin' at one of 'em.
و جنابعالي الان داري به يکيشون ناه مي کني
What do you... What do you want, Brady? I mean, what do you fuckin' want?
تو ي...از من ي مي خواي برادي؟ از جون من ي مي خواي؟
I just want to see my brother, who I love. What's the crime?
مي فقط مي خوام داداشيم رو ببينم جرمه؟
Why couldn't you pick up the phone, and call me, and just ask me to come down,
را مثل آدم تلفن رو برنداشتي و يغام نذاشتي؟ مي تونستي خيلي راحت دعوتم کني بيام اينجا
- like anyone normal person? - Because when I do, you never call me back.
- مثل يه آدم حسابي - ون اه يغام مي ذاشتم، تو هي وقت بهم زن نمي زدي
And, if you did, you'd just say no. Am I lying?
اه هم مي زدي، براي اين بود که بي نميام رت مي م؟
- Well, am I lying? - No. No, you're not.
- رت مي م؟ - نه، نه! نمي ي
- Wow... We ain't bad people, Billy. - I know you're not.
- باباجون...ما آدماي بدي نيستيم بيلي - مي دونم
You know mom put herself in a home?
مي دوني که مامان خودشو برده خونه ي سالمندان؟
- A rest home? - She did. - Jesus.
- خونه ي سالمندان؟ - بعله - !خداي من
You want her to die down here, and you don't even come to say goodbye.
تو مي خواي که اونجا بميره و حتي براي خداحافظي هم بهش سر نزني؟
- Is she still using drugs? - Just go see her and find out for yourself.
- داروهاش رو مي خوره؟ - برو خودت ببين
I can't. I c.. I.. I.. I just can't. I can't go and...
نمي تونم.من...من...من جدي نمي تونم ...نمي تونم برم و
What the hell did any of us ever do that made you hate us this way?
ما ه غلطي کرديم که تو اينقدر ازمون متنفري؟
I don't hate you. I really don't. I just...
ازتون بدم نمياد ...جدا مي م، فقط
And.. And where you're from don't matter to ya? Your family?
و...و اينکه از کجا اومده باشي مهم نيست؟ خونواده ت کيا هستن مهم نيست؟
Your own fuckin' brother?
داداش احمقت مهم نيست؟
Look, I try to live my life with a purposeful measure of control.
ببين، من مي خواستم زنديم هدف داشته باشه
I adhere to certain philosophic tenets that were laid down centuries ago
من به اصول فلسفي باستاني سبيدم که از سال ها يش توي دنيا وجود داشته
by some very introspective thinkers.
و بوسيله متفکرين درون راي بزري مطرح شده بوده
I'm talking about three fucking days in Idabel.
بابا من دارم در مورد ذروندن سه روز لعنتي توي اين شهر صحبت مي کنم
Son of a bitch.
حرومزاده
Ok, look, I will stay through the weekend. But then I'm out of here.
خب، ببين. من تا آخر هفته اينجا مي مونم بعدش مي زنم به اک
Do you understand?
فهميدي؟
Hey! Hey, don't you fuck around. Stop! Jesus!
هي!هي! کرم نريز وايسا، خداي من
God! I think he thought we were selling dime bags.
فکر کنم، تصور مي کرد ما زنبيل مي بافيم
What is all this?
اينا يه؟
Well, let me enlighten you on a point or two.
خب بزار روشنت کنم
It all starts in the mama room. Ya got your young'uns over here,
قصه از اتاق مامان شروع شد شما اسبابتون اينوره
your juvies, and your adults in the back.
به هاتون اينورن بزرترا اونورن
All these lights are sodium-vapor.
تمام اين راغ ها با بخار سديم هستند
Portalux HP 1000 watts
!لاماي 1000 وات
Incandescent's got too much far red in the spectrum.
اين لاما توليد اشعه ي مادون قرمزشون خيلي زياده
Makes the plant grow too tall on the stem,
که باعث رشد ياهان در راستاي نور ميشه
and the leaves get all nine, and the whole thing just keels over.
و بر ها که کاملا سترده مي شوند ياه دَمَرو مي شود
Plus, it reduces the potency, which is definitely not what we want.
به اضافه ي اينکه توان جنسيش هم کاهش يدا مي کند که مطلوب ما نيست
Now, LED's gettin' to be all the rage
طرفدار بيشتري دارد LED اين روزا لام
'cause it's cooler and saves ya on power costs, but...
ون حرارت کمتري توليد مي کند و هزينه ي کمتري هم دارد
Ya know, we got your electronic digital balance
ما متعادل کننده ي ديجيتال برق تو رو هم قرض رفتيم
Hey, raise 'er up, Bolger!
ببرش بالا، بالر
- Who built all this? - Me and Bolger.
- کي اينا رو سَرِهم کرده؟ - من و بالر
Had a few buddies help us with the heavy liftin'.
براي وسايل سنين تر هم ند تا از به ها بهمون کمک کردند
Your brother designed every bit of it.
داداشت همه يز رو خودش طراحي کرده
The horticultural part.
بخش باغبوني
Quonset, ah, comes in a fuckin' catalog kit. Grade-schoolers could've assembled it.
اينا از روي کاتالوشون بستيم يه به ي دبستاني هم مي تونه اينا رو سرهم کنه
We should've got a contractor to pour the pad,
ما بايد براي بخش آب اشي يک يمانکار مي رفتيم
but we couldn't likely hire one of those, could we?
ولي علاقه اي به استخدام اينجور افراد نداريم، منظورم رو فهميدي؟
- And, and, what... what are all these? - Oh, NFT Spiral System. - NFT?
- و اينا...اينا ديه يه؟ - NFT اوه، سيستم حلزوني - NFT?
Yea, nutrient film technique.
تکنيک تغذيه ي غشايي
No soil in there. These pipes are filled with hydroclay.
يعني با خاک معمولي وشيده نشده ر شده Hydroclay اين لوله ها با
It's like an expanded clay aggregate, supports the active capillaries.
نوعي خاک حاوي سندانه است
It's just that and coconut husks, if you can believe that shit.
که علاوه بر اون، حاوي وست ناريل هم هست اه حرفام رو بتوني هضم کني
No acid, no alkaline in the base, totally sterile medium.
نه اسيديه و نه قليايي خنثي pH استريل همراه با
You're lookin' at cell generation of hybridization cloning,
تو داري به نسل جديدي از کلونين سلول هاي دوره  ناه مي کني
through all my special little children.
مثل به هام مي مونند
And we feed ya good, too, don't we?
و ما خيلي خوب بهشون مي رسيم، مه نه؟
Pump the nutrients, see, up into the medium from underneath.
ما مواد مغذي رو به داخل محيط از ائين م مي کنيم
Big Bud, Connoisseur, Nirvana, Jungle Juice, Tarantula, the whole shitteroo.
هر مدل ماده مخدر طبيعي
You're looking at the motherfuckin' state of the art.
تو داري به يک شاهکار هنري ناه مي کني
I don't know what to say.
نمي دونم ي بايد بم
You hear that, Bolger, we rendered him speechless! Huh!
شنيدي بالر؟ ما اونو از حرف زدن انداختيم
- You wanna try some? - No
- مي خواي يکمي امتحان کني؟ - نه
I make my living with my mind, and, so, I like to keep it clear.
من با افکارم خرجم رو در ميارم س ترجيح مي دهم سالم بمونند
I forgot who I was talking to.
يه لحظه يادم رفت کي جلوم وايستاده
Traveling through his optic space-time. Shit.
محصور توي افکار عتيقه ي ند تا آدم مرده ندت بزنه
Let's go sit on the back porch. I've got a new varietal.
بريم حياط عقبي من ند تا محصول جديد دارم
I really gotta give her a test drive.
که بايد تستشون کنم
Now, I read an article you wrote in the New York Review of Books,
يه مقاله ازت توي خوندم New York Review of Books
- 'bout a fellow called Heidegigger. - Heidegger?
- در مورد يه بابايي به اسم هايدير (يک فيلسوف معروف آلماني) بود - هايدير؟
That's the one. What kind of name is that?
خودشه اين ديه ه جور اسميه
Exactly! That right there is what I don't understand about y'all! I mean...
دقيقا، ببين اين همون يزيه که من در مورد تو نمي فهمم ...منظورم اينه که
Y'all ever... hardly ever write about a topic!
تو خيلي...خيلي موضوع رو مي يوني
I mean, you write about what some other fellow wrote about the topic.
مثلا در مورد بابايي مي نويسي که خودش در مورد !يه باباي ديه نوشته
So, so Heidegger's got some idea, and then some, some French guy's got a take on that,
يعني هايدير شما يه ايده اي داشته بعد يه باباي فرانسوي مياد رو اون يه ايده ي ديه ميده
then you write a review of that,
بعد تو روي اون يه ايده مي دي
and some other fellow's gonna come along and on and on and on and on.
بعد يکي ديه روي ايده ي تو يه ايده ميده همين جوري ايده ست که مي اشه روي ورق
You very neatly explained academia, Brady.
تو تحصيلات آکادميک رو خيلي ساده حساب مي کني برادي
So, I'll write and say for all y'all.
خب، من يه جوري مي نويسم و حرف ميزنم که همه بفهمند
It's just called, "What the Fuck's the Point"?
الان هم منظورم اينه که نکته ي لعنتي اين قصه کجاست؟
Ya know what? I think this is right about where I leave.
مي دوني يه؟ اين دقيقا مربوط به همون قسمتيه که توش من الان ول  مي کنم و بر مي ردم
Come on, come on.
بي خيال، بي خيال
- Give you a tug on that. - I said no.
- بيا يه دمي بزن - فتم نه
You used to do this more'n I did. You couldn't get enough of it.
تو که از من بيشتر ميزدي اونقدري نيست که تو يکي رو بيره
Well, I just don't do it anymore.
درسته، اما ديه نمي خوامش
Oh, I know you want some. It's written all over your face.
اوه، تابلوهه که بهش احتياج داري
Look, the shit I grow is better than anything you're gonna taste anywhere.
ببين، اوني که من اون شت عمل ميارم از هر يزي که قبلا زدي بهتره
Makes that Jamaica shit we used to buy taste like tobacco.
باعث ميشه اون آشغال جامائيکايي که قبلا مي رفتيم مزه ي تنباکو بده
Oh, I'll bet it does.
شرط مي بندم همين طوره
A tiny taste. A little, little, bitty, ole taste. Just.. Taste!
يه کامه کوولو بير يه کامه خيلي خيلي کوولو
Fine, fine. Fuck, I don't believe I'm doing this. This is so fucking stupid!
باشه، باشه باورم نميشه هميين حماقتي رو دوباره مي کنم
When was the last time you did it?
آخرين بار کي اين حماقتو کردي؟
- Graduate school. - I'll bet this is gonna lay you out.
- دبيرستان - س فکر کنم بزنتت
- You remember the first time? With ma? - I remember.
- اولين بار رو يادته؟ با مامان؟ - آره
[Both] Fucking ridiculous.
مسخره ست
I guess she just figured we were gonna find out on our own, anyway.
فکر کنم فهميده بود که مي خوايم روي اي خودمون وايسيم
I... I don't wanna know what she was thinking about.
نمي خوام...نمي خوام بدونم به ي فکر مي کرده
Oh, come on, give it a real pull there.
بي خيال بابا، يه کام اساسي بير
Now, how many buds are you gonna smoke that's that
اه بم اين به اندازه مدتي که تو نبودي
smooth after you ain't done it in a number of years?
زمان برده تا عمل بياد، ي مي ي؟
I've been lengthening the maturing process more in the Dutch tradition,
من به سنت فرانسوي ها زمان عمل آوردنش رو طولاني تر کردم
- and I got just the right amount of resin. - Wow!
- و شيره ي خدايي ازش کشيدم - !خدا جون
Ooohhh! Now we're cookin'.
آهااااا! تازه داريم رم مي شيم
So, anyways, I seem to recall you didn't..
...خب، فکر کنم تو ديه
you didn't think too much of this fellow, Heidegigger.
ديه الان يزي از اين هايدينرتون يادت نياد...
What? No, he was a fucking fascist. He... He held down the National Socialists.
ي؟ نه بابا، اون يه فاشيست احمق بود اون...اون جامعه شناسي ملل را خراب کرد
All right, but this article was about logic and... and truth, and
قبول، ولي اين مقاله در مورد منطق و...حقيقت بود
about him and some other fellow related to, uh...
...در مورد خودش و يه يارويي که مربوط بود به، اوه
- Analytic philosophy. - What was it? - Analytic philosophy.
- !اره شناسيه فلسفي - اين ديه ي بود؟ - اره شناسي فلسفي
Analytic philosophy.
اره شناسي فلسفي
There was one word I didn't know. I had to look it up. Epista...
يه کلمه اي بود که تا حالا نشنيده بودم ...مجبور شدم توي ديکشنري دنبالش بردم، معرفت
- Epistemology. - Epista what? - Epistemology.
- معرفت شناسي - معرفت ي؟
Epistemology, bingo, bingo.
معرفت شناسي ايول، ايول
Why are we talking about this?
حالا را داريم در مورد اين يزا صحبت مي کنيم؟
Just solving problems.
داريم مشکلات جهان رو حل مي کنيم
Like... Like, when all of a sudden, you get hit with a answer,
مثلا...مثلا وقتي که با مشکلي دريري و ...جواب يهو مي کوبه به ذهن
to a mess you've been in,
...آشفته ات...
and as soon as it hit ya, ya can't hardly believe ya didn't think of it before.
و وقتي که کوبيد، تازه به اين فکر مي افتي که اي بابا اين که خيلي ساده بود، را قبلا به ذهنم نرسيد
What is it you want, Brady?
دنبال ي هستي برادي؟
- Here, git ya another pull on that. - No, I'm fucking euthanized.
- بيا، يه کام ديه بير - نه، من ديه داغون شدم
Go on, now. Go on!
بيا، بيا بيا
All right, now, here's the thing.
خيلي خب، برنامه اينه
All that equipment you see out yonder. It was expensive.
بساطي که اون طرف ديدي خيلي رون تموم شد
So I had to go see this Jew up in Tulsa, who's kinda in the business.
س براش مجبور شدم به ديدن يه يهودي که کارش اين بود، برم
- What do ya mean, he's in the business? - Well, the dope dealing business.
- يعني ي که کارش اين بود؟ - تجارت مواد مخدر
A Jew in the business? How do ya know he's a Jew?
يهودي و تجارت مواد؟ از کجا فهميدي يهوديه؟
Well, he... Trust me, he's a Jew.
خب ببين...باور کن يهوديه
Well, what does that mean? He has a Jewish last name?
خب، حالا که ي؟ فاميليش به يهودي ها مي خورد؟
He's a goddamn Jew!
!بابا اون يه يهودي لعنتي بود، همين
- Don't be anti-Semitic. - Anti what? - Anti-Jew.
- ضد يهودي نباش - ضد يهود؟ - ضد يهود
I ain't anti-Jew! I loves everybody!
نيستم من همه رو دوست دارم
Oh, Jesus! So, okay, he's a dope dealer. So what...
خب، بذريم اون دلال مواد بود، بعد؟
Well, he's not really a dealer. He's... He's a little more upstream than that,
...خب مي دوني؟ واقعا هم دلال نبود يکمي از اون بالاتر بود
but I've been his main supplier of grass.
ولي من توليد کننده ي اول اون توي حشيش شدم
- I still don't see... - Will ya listen? Ya just..
- ...من هنوز مطلبو نر - ...وش مي کني؟ همش
Ya know, ya never listen!
مي دوني، حرف ميزني و وش نمي کني
Okay, okay, fine, I'm listening.
باشه، باشه وش مي کنم
I need you to be me.
مي خوام که من بشي
What?
ي؟
Down here, just like we used to back at home,
من بشي، مثل قديما، جاي من بري خونه
while I go up there and figure out this whole situation.
تا وقتي که من برم و اين مشکل رو حل کنم
No fucking chance, Brady.
عمرا، برادي
Well, look, I've got this one figured. It's so simple.
خب، ببين. من همين راه به ذهنم رسيد ...خيلي ساده ست
All you gotta do is go and visit mom.
تمام کاري که بايد بکني اينه که بري مامان رو ببيني...
You don't think mom is gonna know the difference between you and me?
فکر ميکني مامان فرق من و تو رو نمي دونه؟
It ain't about mom, goddamn it. It's the sheriff. It's he we're gonna fool.
بابا قضيه سر مامان نيست خدا خفه ت کنه کلانتره، مي خوام که اون فريب بخوره
We don't even look alike, anymore. Has that occurred to you?
ما که ديه شبيه هم نيستيم تا حالا متوجهش نشدي؟
Bolger said when you walked into that Me Tote Em, it took all of
...بالر بهم فت که وقتي داخل کافه شدي
five seconds for them boys to figure out it was me with a shave and haircut.
نج ثانيه طول کشيد که به ها باور کنند که اين من هستم که سر و صورتم رو اصلاح کردم
- Which is why he took me to Broken Bow. - He said you wanted to go.
- آها س براي همين من رو اونجا برد - فتش خودت خواستي بري
Brady, Brady, I swear to God, even for you...
...برادي، برادي، به خدا قسم اه اين کار فکر
Well, that might have been Bolger's idea,
...خب خب، ممکنه که ايده ي بالر بوده باشه
but I didn't know nothing about it till you all showed up here.
ولي عمرا نمي دونستم اون اتفاق مي افته
And let me tell you something else. We're going back up to Broken Bow,
و بزار بهت يه يزي بم ما بايد دوباره اونجا بررديم
and we're gonna whip some country ass.
و وزه ي ند نفر رو به خاک بماليم
No, no, you're not.
نه، نه اصلا امکان نداره
Started without us?
بدون ما شروع کردين؟
Well, you know you can't have none of this good stuff.
خب، تو ميدوني که الان نمي توني از اينا بزني
I know, but I'm being polite. The rest of 'em came.
مي دونم، ولي مي خوام که مهمون نوازي کنم بقيه که هستن
That is so weird.
خيلي جالبه
Oh, Janet, this is my dear brother, Bill. Bill, this is our good friend, Janet.
ژانت، اين داداشي ل من، بيله بيل، اين هم دوست خوبه ما، ژانت
- Hi, I'm Bill. - You havin' a smoke? - Oh, I wa... I was, yea.
- سلام - يزي زدي؟ - اوه بله...بله
- Oh, uh, do you want some? - Oh, I'm gonna get a beer, thanks.
- شما هم مي خواين؟ -  من آبجو مي خوام
Yea, I... I... I usually don't, either. I... I...
آره، من...من معمولا نمي کشم ...من...من
Actually, actually, I never do. I... I'm...
....حقيقتش، حقيقتش ...هي وقت
It's all right. Nobody can say no to Brady.
درکت مي کنم، هي کسي به برادي نه نميه
Mojo, I got the mojo.
همه رو طلسم مي کنم
I kinda forgot.
يادم رفته بود
So, Bolger says you're a famous, what was it you said, Bolger?
راستي، بالر فتش شما خيلي معروف هستيد ي فته بودي؟
- A famous thinker.
- انديشمند بزر
- He's real famous. - In certain esoteric circles, aught maybe.
- خيلي معروفه - تو بعضي زمينه ها شايد معروف باشم
And they pay you for that?
ول هم توش هست؟
Well, I... I... I lecture, and I... I teach. I am a professor.
خب، راستش من...من...من سخنراني مي کنم و درس مي دهم. من استاد دانشاه هستم
- I was just fuckin' with you. - Ah, you're... Yea... - Nice to meet you.
- سرکارت ذاشتم - ...آها، شما...شما - خوشحال شدم
- She's a poet. - What? - Seriously, she writes fuckin' poetry.
- اون شاعره - ي؟ - جدي مي م، شعر ميه
And she's the ladies noodling champion of '05.
جايزه هم برده
125 pounds of catfish, in under 10 hours, with nothing but her bare hands.
يه ربه ماهي 125 وندي رو زير 10 ساعت با دست خالي رفته
I tried to get her and Colleen in a three-way once,
خواستم هم اون هم کالين رو با هم بخوابونم
but wouldn't neither of 'em go for it.
اما منم زورم نرسيد
- I'm... I'm leaving on Sunday, you do understand that, right? - I understand that.
- من يکشنبه مي رم، مي فهمي که؟ - مي فهمم
- I am not gonna participate... - No, no, we'll talk about that later.
- ...من دخالتي توي - نه، نه. حالا بعدا صحبت مي کنيم
Hey, Bolger, crank her up, man!
آهاي، بالر کرم نريز
All this happened in one day.
همه اين برنامه ها بايد توي يه روز اتفاق بيفته؟
Almost everything that has happened here has only served to vindicate why I stay away.
همه ي يزايي که تا الان اتفاق افتاد دليل ترک کردن اين محل براي من بود
Oh, come on. Don't tell me that goblet of goodness in your hand hadn't made ya happy.
بيخيال، اينقدر وانمود نکن که با يزي که توي دستته بهت خوش نمي ذره
No, even that, whatever it actually is.
حتي با اين هم که، اسمشو نمي دونم هم، نمي ذره
That's Ambrosia, Billy. That's pure Ambrosia.
اين مائده ي بهشتيه مائده ي بهشتيه
Oh, ride the blue wind high and free, she'll lead you down through misery,
Oh, ride the blue wind high and free, she'll lead you down through misery,
Leave you low, come time to go, alone and low as low can be.
Leave you low, come time to go, alone and low as low can be.
Well, if I had a nickel, I'd find a game. If I won a dollar, I'd make it rain.
Well, if I had a nickel, I'd find a game. If I won a dollar, I'd make it rain.
If it rained an ocean, I'd drink it dry, lay me down dissatisfied.
If it rained an ocean, I'd drink it dry, lay me down dissatisfied.
Oh, legs to walk and thoughts to fly, eyes to laugh...
Oh, legs to walk and thoughts to fly, eyes to laugh...
- So, where do you live now? - Mmm, Providence, Rhode Island.
- الان کجا هستي؟ - Providence, Rhode Island.
- Why, why would you come back here? - It's where I wanna write.
- را، را دوباره به اينجا برشتي؟ - دوست دارم در موردش بنويسم
- I teach for money. - Is it a college? - High school, here in town.
- براي اينکه خرجم در بياد، درس مي دم - توي دانشاه؟ - دبيرستان، توي شهر
High school?
دبيرستان؟
I tried the tenure track, but college students are already
مشاوره ي تحصيلي دانشاه رو مي خواستم ...ولي دانشجوها قبلا
too culturally informed. Closes their minds.
براي اين قسمت آماده شده بودند و ذهنشون ذيراي مطالب جديد نبود
How come there aren't more girls, like you, writing Hugo?
طوريه که ديه دخترايي مثل تو کم يدا مي شوند که سبک هوو (ويکتور هوو) بنويسند؟
Maybe they don't know how to look.
شايد ون ديد مناسبي به قضيه ندارند
Well, you... you teach... English?
خب تو...انليسي درس ميدي؟
- I do. - Hmm...
- آره
- My mother used to do that for awhile. - She must be very proud of you.
- مادر من هم مدتي اينکار رو مي کرد - حتما بهت خيلي افتخار مي کنه
- I haven't talked to her in quite awhile. - Why not?
- خيلي وقته باهاش صحبت نکرده ام - را؟
That is a very complicated subject.
قصه اش مفصله
- You're some world-famous thinker? - Har... Hardly
- تو يکي از بزرترين انديشمندان دنيايي؟ - شا...شايد
Some minorly famous thinker?
يکي از معدود متفکرين معروف؟
- And you don't let your mother enjoy that? - That's correct.
- و نمي ذاري که مادر خودت از مصاحبت با تو بهره مند بشه؟ - درسته
It's not good to have unresolved problems with your mother.
خوب نيست که رابطه تون به اين شکل باقي بمونه
- Why? - Because some day, she'll be gone. Then where will you be?
- را؟ - براي اينکه يه روزي اون از اين دنيا ميره و اونوقت تو کجايي؟
- Probably the same place I am right now. - Exactly.
- احتمالا همين جايي که هستم - دقيقا
- You're smart. - You aren't as smart as you think you are.
- تو هم زرني ها - اما تو اونقدري که فکر مي کني هم باهوش نيستي
Well, hey, I just got tricked by my dope-dealing brother.
خب، درسته. ون فريب برادر مواد فروشم رو خوردم
We all get tricked some time or other.
همه مون يه زماني فريب يه يزي رو مي خوريم
- Mmm, I don't think so. - No? - No - Why?
- فکر نکنم بشه - جدا؟ - نه - را؟
A combination of what you've been smoking and what I'd do with you.
ون اه يزي که تو دود کردي و من با تو انجام بدم رو با هم ترکيب کنيم
You'd never recover.
ممکنه ديه حالت جا نياد
I'll do my best.
من کارمو خوب بلدم
I'm goin' home.
بهتره برم خونه
Well, can't light a cake. Can... could we just like, um...
خب، ظاهرا کاسب نيستيم ...ميشه...فقط مثل
I mean, we were, we were kind of lost... having a hug.
منظورم اينه که ما، ما يه جورايي مثل هم هستيم
I'm going noodling tomorrow, if you want to tag along.
من فردا ميرم ماهييري، اه ايه هستي
My brother said that you did that.
برادرم فت که سررميته
Sweet dreams.
خوب بخوابي
Here you go.
بفرمائيد
Check out the best part.
اينجا رو داشته باش
- Holy shit! - This here's why I keep it alive.
- ايول بابا - اينجورياست که مين کارمون درسته
- Wait a minute. Some of these are from our room. - Oh, yea.
- صبر کن ببينم، بعضي از اينا مال اتاق سابقمونه - درسته
Yup, a few more I picked up along the road, but all originals. Ain't no knockoffs.
آره، يک سري هاشم، از اينور اونور جور شده هنوز کار داره
- Wow - Now sit you down.
- واي - حالا بشين
Ain't that the coup de grace? I got her off from Taylor in Ponca City,
جير کُش نيست؟ از تِيلور رفتمش
before me and Colleen hooked up. That was my deal closer, baby.
قبل از اينکه منو کالين با هم جور بشيم کمک کرد کارمون (حاملي) جلو بيفته
If Colleen knew what went on in that bed, she'd never let me [indistinct].
اه کالين مي دونست ه کارايي رو ي اين تخت کردم ترتيبمو مي داد
- Lovely. - Let's get you somethin' for that buzz you got workin'.
- جالبه - بزار يزايي رو نشونت بدم که تکونت بده
- Hey! Remember this? - You still goin' with vinyl, huh?
- اينو يادته؟ - هنوز با اين صفحه ها حال مي کني؟
Oh, hell, yea! I don't go in for no digital. They can't improve a phono classics man.
بله قربان، اين به سيستم ديجيتال شرف داره اونا نمي تونن منو از دنياي خودم جدا کنند
- Come on, lay you down. - Lie down.
- بيخيال، بک - بخواب
- Now you sound like mom. - Sorry.
- مثل مامان حرف ميزني - ببخشيد
Lady in a turban, a cocaine tree
Lady in a turban, a cocaine tree
- How's that for a lullaby [indistinct]. - Ahhh...
- براي لالايي طوره؟ - ...آه ه ه ه
Does a dance so rhythmically
Does a dance so rhythmically
Hey, don't think that this means that I'm in any way...
...فکر نمي کني که اين باعث بشه من اون برنامه رو
We ain't gonna talk about that right now.
بعدا در موردش صحبت مي کنيم
Having a time
Having a time
I'm just glad you're here, Billy.
خوشحالم که اينجايي
Cocaine tree lookin' fine
Cocaine tree lookin' fine
Gotta put on your sailin' shoes.
Gotta put on your sailin' shoes.
Put on your sailin' shoes
Put on your sailin' shoes
Everyone will start to cheer
Everyone will start to cheer
When you put on your sailin' shoes
When you put on your sailin' shoes
Doctor, doctor, ahhh
Doctor, doctor, ahhh
Oh, cut it out.
دستتو بکش
How ya feelin', professor?
طوري استاد؟
- Mmmm, what did you do? - Well, I bumped into some clippers.
- ه کردي؟ - سيستمو عوض کردم
Hmm, feels weird.
حس عجيبي دارم
- Whaddya think? - Ahhh...
- نظرت يه؟
- Oh, God. What time is it? - It's time to get up.
- خداجون، ساعت نده؟ - وقت بلند شدنه
Here, I bought you a few things. Put 'em on.
بيا برات ند تا لباس رفتم، بوش
What? Why?
ي؟ را؟
Remember that thing we were talkin' about [indistinct].
يادته ي بهت فته بودم؟
- No, no, Brady. That's... that's just not gonna work. - Why?
- نه، نه، نه برادي، اين غيرممکنه - را؟
Well, for one thing, because you've given
...خب يه دليلش اون مدل
yourself the stupidest haircut in human history.
موي مسخره ايه که تو براي خودت داشتيه
Oh, bullshit, you ain't that fancy. Can't hardly tell the difference.
اينا همش رنده خودتم نمي توني تفاوتمون رو بي
No, I'm... I'm sorry, I never said...
...نه من...ببخشيد، من نفتم
Haven't I fixed you up with Janet? And then you like her?
ببينم مه من کارتو با ژانت رديف نکردم؟ و تو هم ازش خوشت اومد؟
My opinion of her is totally unrelated to your infantile scheme.
عقيده ي من نسبت به اون با اين برنامه ي به ونه ي سرکار خيلي فرق داره
You listen!
وش کن
I ain't foolin'. You gotta help me, because if I don't get up to Tulsa,
من ديوونه نشدم، تو بايد به من کمک کني ...ون اه تولسا نرم
I'm gonna be in some real trouble.
اوضاعمون خيلي بي ريخت ميشه...
Then go up to Tulsa. Why do I have to...
خب همينجوري برو تولسا ...را من بايد
Because some shit might happen in Tulsa to where I...
...ون اتفاقاتي ممکنه توي تولسا بيفته که بهتره من
Where... Where you would rather be seen down here, so that you're not implicated in
که...که جنابعالي ترجيح ميديد وقتي اتفاق ميفته، اينجا ديده شده باشيد
whatever typically insane criminal behavior that you intend.
و از هرونه اتهامي مُبرا بشيد
No fucking way!
عمرا
All I'm askin' you to do is go and see mom.
تمام يزي که من ازت مي خوام اينه که اشي بري مامان رو ببيني
That one little good deed. That's all.
اين فقط يه کار خيره همين
Well, it's not a good deed, and I really don't wanna see mom.
نه اين کاره خير نيست و بنده هم نمي خوام مامان رو ببينم
You come all the way down here!
بابا اين همه راه رو تا اينجا، الکي که نيومدي
No! No! You tricked me into coming, actually.
نه، نه! تو سر من کلاه ذاشتي
Oh! Please! It's... It's so simple!
تو رو خدا! اين که کاري نداره
All you gotta do is walk into a fucking rest home
...تمومه کاري که بايد بکني اينه که بري خونه ي سالمندان
and see your own mother you ain't seen in 12 years, for God knows why!
و مامانتو که 12 ساله خدا ميدونه را نديدي، ببيني...
I don't know why you wanna pass a pig eatin' a bear claw.
نمي دونم را اينقدر از اينکه يه خيکي بطري بدست ببينتت مي ترسي
They don't call them that anymore.
اونا ديه اينجوري صداشون نمي کنند
- What? - Nope! They aren't called pigs anymore. That's exactly...
- ي؟ - ...ديه اونا رو خيکي صدا نمي کنند. بهش
Called the police.
بهشون مين ليس
How do you even know that he'll be there?
اصلا تو از کجا ميدوني ليسه اونجاست؟
'Cuz he's got a shine on his heifer who sits behind the desk.
ون وساله اي که ازش خوشش مياد شت ميز اونجا ميشينه
All you gotta do is walk in and say, "Hi, ya, Sharon. I'm goin' to see my ma."
تمومه کاري که بايد بکني اينه که بري و بي "سلام شارون، اومدم مادرم رو ببينم"
And don't say another fuckin' word. And just walk on by.
اونا هم يه کلمه باهات حرفي نمي زنند و راحت ميري تو
That is the most ridiculous alibi.
اين احمقانه ترين بهونه ي دنياست
All anyone would have to do is find out that you have a twin and that I was down here.
بالاخره يکي اونجا هست که بفهمه تو يک قُلِ ديه هم داري و تصادفا اون هم توي اين شهره
When we ever been busted before? You took tests for me all the time.
آخرين بار کي با هم ير افتاديم؟ تو سر همه ي امتحان ها هم جاي من مي رفتي
- And I let you go on dates as me. - No, I did that one time when we were 16.
- منم ميزاشتم جاي من با دخترا بري بيرون - نخير، همش يک دفعه بود و اونم من 16 سالم بيشتر نبود
- And she guzzled your custard, didn't she? - I have felt bad about that ever since.
- و اصلا هم بهت نسبيد؟ - من حس بدي دارم
Come on, Billy. I'm trying to change my life here.
بيخيال بيلي من دارم زور مي زنم اوضاعمون رو يه تکوني بدم
- Fucking hell. - I'm asking, as your brother.
- مشو بابا - به عنوان داداشت ازت مي خوام
Ugg.. I just walk by.
ببين...من فقط ميرم اونجا
I got kicked off of Noah's Ark I turn my cheek to unkind remarks
I got kicked off of Noah's Ark I turn my cheek to unkind remarks
There was two of everything but one of me
There was two of everything but one of me
- Say, ain't it Saturday? - Yeah, so?
- ببينم، امروز شنبه ست؟ - آره، که ي؟
Think the Jews is in church Saturdays. You know where it's at?
فکر کنم امروز يهودي ها توي کنيسه هستند تو جاشو مي دوني؟
- Can't we look it up? - What if it's more'n one?
- کاري نداره، مي رم يداش مي کنيم - اه از يکي بيشتر باشه ي؟
There can't be more than one.
نمي تونه بيشتر از يه دونه توي اين شهر باشه
- Can I ask you a question? - Shoot
- يه سوال برسم؟ - بفرما
Do you believe in a higher power?
تو به خدا عقيده داري؟
Yea, I do. I do. It's the only way to make sense of all this.
بلي، دارم، دارم ون تنها دليليه که بساط اين دنيا رو منطقي نشون ميده
Otherwise, it's just pure fucking chaos.
غير از اين، همه يز به هم مي ريخت
Like, the world was created by Him, and He judges what we do?
يعني عقيده ت اين جوريه که خدا دنيا رو آفريد و حواسش به کارهاي ماست؟
No, I think it's more like, like parallel lines.
نه، بيشتر اين رابطه رو به شکل موازي مي بينم
Parallel lines?
موازي؟
Ya know, like two lines go on and on forever and don't ever touch.
شنيدي که مين دو تا خط موازي کنار هم حرکت مي کنند ولي هي وقت به هم نمي رسند
Yea
آره
'Cept, 'cept they don't actually exist in nature.
دو تا خط موازي در طبيعت واقعا وجود ندارند
And man can't create no true parallel. It's just more of a concept.
کسي نمي تونه اونا رو واقعا درست کنه اين حرفا فقط مفهوميه
I learned that shit in high school geometry.
من اين رو سر کلاس هندسه ديبرستان ياد رفته بودم
Ah huh
آها
Well, that concept, that perfection...
...اين همون مفهوم و کماليه که
We know it exists, and we think about it.
ما مي دونيم هست و در موردش فکر مي کنيم...
But we can't never get there ourselves.
اما هيوقت بهش نمي رسيم
I think that right there is God.
به نظر من اين تعريف خداست
- You ready? - For what? - Come on over here.
- آماده اي؟ - براي ي؟ - بيا کمک
- Jesus! - You just gonna stand there?
- خدايا - مي خواي همينجور وايسي
You have a spiritual aversion to monofilament?
تو به قلاب ماهييري اصلا عقيده اي نداري؟
This is the way it was done a thousand years ago.
اين روشي بود که هزاران سال يش باهاش ماهي مي رفتند
I think I can understand that.
حالا مي فهمم
You still leavin' tomorrow?
هنوز مي خواي فردا برردي؟
I think so.
احتمالا
- I'll miss you. - And we barely even know each other.
- دلم برات تن ميشه - در حاليکه ما خيلي کم همدير رو مي شناسيم
You have not known what you are.
You have not known what you are. (شعر ميه)
You have slumbered upon yourself all your life.
You have slumbered upon yourself all your life.
Your eyelids have been the same as closed most of the time.
Your eyelids have been the same as closed most of the time.
What you have done returns already in mockeries.
What you have done returns already in mockeries.
The mockeries are not you.
The mockeries are not you.
Underneath them and within them, I see you lurk.
Underneath them and within them, I see you lurk.
- Who is that? - Walt Whitman
- از کي بود؟ - والت وايتمن
I don't think I ever imagined hearing him recited to me by a
...هي وقت فکر نمي کردم شعرش رو
girl getting a 40-pound catfish.
از يه دختري که توي دستش يه ماهي !هل وندي نه داشته، بشنوم
That's exactly how he should be recited. He wrote without rhyme or meter.
اتفاقا شعراي اون رو بايد همينجوري خوند اون بدون هي وزن و قافيه اي شعر مي فت
Free verse... just whatever he felt inside,
...راحت همون يزي که حس مي کرد رو به شعر مي فت
coming out in his own intricate rhythm.
ريتم ييده اي براي خودش داشت
Pure, unashamed passion, without definable restriction.
زلال، بدون احساس ناه بدون هي حد و مرزي
- I'm sorry, see, I ha.. have a few issues with that. - Why?
- ببخشيد، ولي من باهاش ند تا مشکل دارم - را؟
Because some have dared to suggest that even poetry has rules.
ون بعضي افراد عقيده دارند که شعر قوانين خاص خودش رو هميشه داره
Or you make your own.
و ار هم نداشت، تو بايد برايش بسازي
Right there, that's the part I never bought into.
خب، اين از اون حرفاست که توي کَتِ من نميره
- Because? - Because if everybody runs around, making their own rules,
- را؟ - ون اه هر کي از راه رسيد ...و خواست قوانين خودش رو وارد شعر کنه
how can you find what's true?
اونوقت ه جوري مي تونيم حقيقت شعر رو بفهميم؟...
There's nothing... There's nothing to rely on.
...اون وقت ديه هي يزي هي يزي براي استناد بهش نيست
One night,
One night, (شعر ميه)
I [indistinct],
I [indistinct],
devoured your leaves,
devoured your leaves,
knowing no poison, no love nourishment
knowing no poison, no love nourishment
in that larval blindness, a hunger finally true.
in that larval blindness, a hunger finally true.
- Who's that? - That's me.
- مال کي بود؟ - مال خودم
Maybe what's true is in front of us,
...ممکنه که حقيقت جلوي شم ما باشه
and we're moving toward it without even knowing it's there.
و ما به سمتش حرکت کنيم بدون اينکه بدونيم اونجاست
Once you think you've got it all solved,
وقتي که فکر کني همه اسخ ها رو داري
what's left?
ديه ي ميمونه؟
Don't get any fish innards on me, okay?
از اون دل و روده هاي ماهي !يزي به من نمالي ها
Shut up.
خفه شو
So, what is the Halakhah?
س هالاخاه يست؟
It's the law.
قانونه
It's the path we follow in our daily lives.
اين همون روشيه که ما در زنديه روزمره مون بايد در يش بيريم
It comprises those rituals that make our lives complete.
شامل مراسمي ست که حيات ما را کامل مي کند
Without them, the violence and anarchy of the world prevail.
بدون آنها،خشونت و بي نظمي بر دنيا مسلط مي شود
When Moses talks with God on Sinai,
هنامي که موسي با خداوند در سينا صحبت مي کرد
the Jews abandoned the law,
بني اسرائيل از قوانين سريي کردند
and danced ecstatically before the calf,
و در يش روي وساله با سرخوشي رقصيدند
forgetting the one who brought them out of Egypt.
و رها دهنده شان از مصر را فراموش کردند
My friends, in every generation, we are threatened
دوستان من، بزر و کوک، ما رهانيده شديم از
with chaos and slavery and despair.
از بي نظمي، بردي و نااميدي
And then this... this spirit and confusion.
و اين...اين غرور و مشتي
Halakhah allows refuge in a world we can't explain.
هالاخاه ناهاه امن ما در اين دنياست
Violence, anarchy
خشونت، هرج و مرج
in which the workings of justice may falter, there is a larger and deeper coherence.
کارزاران عدالت را ممکن ست به لکنت بياندازد ولي در اينجا عامل بزرتر و عميقتري وجود دارد
Who the fuck is that?
اين ديه کيه؟
To know this with certainty is to belief as a Jew.
براي درک کامل، بايد به يهوديت معتقد بود
Without law, we are lost
بدون قوانين يهود، ما م شده ايم
Fuckin' faggot.
عجب کَنه ايه
in an arid wasteland. No good to each other.
در اين دنياي بي حاصل بدون خوبي به يکدير
Not this mess
بزن به اک
No good to our God.
بدون کار نيکي براي روردار
- Shabbat Shalom - AUDIENCE: Shabbat Shalom
- آمين - حضار: آمين
So, I would like to thank the Taubmann family
در ضمن مي خواستم از خانواده ي تابومَن تشکر کنم
for the beautiful flowers that adorn our bema,
براي اين ل هاي زيبا که منبر ما رو آراسته کردند
- Thanks for doing this. - Happy to.
- ممنون براي همراهيت - خواهش مي کنم
All right.
خب
- You sure you don't wanna come in? - I'll be waitin' right over there.
- جدا نمي خواي بياي داخل؟ - اونور منتظر ميمونم
But will look kindly later on boys who sort shit out with their mamas.
!ولي حواسم به سرايي که با مامانشون بد حرف بزنند هست
How do I look?
ه جوري شدم؟
Well, hi ya, Sharon, just goin' to see my mom.
سلام شارون، فقط اومدم مامانمو ببينم
Officer
سرکار
Oh, oh, oh, ah! Whoa! Whoa! Whoa! Whoa! Wait! Wait!
اوه اوه اوه، باباااااا، صبر کن، صبر کن
Oh, okay, okay, hang on, man!
خب، خب، خب...وايسا بابا
No, no, not a word from you, Brady, you hear, you're just gonna listen.
نه، نه، يک کلمه هم حرف نزن برادي فقط وش کن ببين ي مي م
The staff here, they found your mama smokin' pot the other day.
بروبه ها ديروز مامانتو ديدند که داشته حشيش دود مي کرده
Now she's a crazy lady, don't even belong in here,
حالا که قاطي داره، ديه اينجا نبايد بمونه
but it wouldn't do nobody no good to put her away.
ولي براي ما خوبيت نداره که خودمون بندازيمش بيرون
The only reason I ain't haulin' you in is 'cuz
تنها دليلي که نيومدم بندازمت هلفدوني اينه که
I ain't got proof it was you give it to her.
هنوز مدرکي دستم نرسيده که تو اون آشغالا رو دستش دادي
As soon as I do, we gonna get on your property and we gonna
و وقتي بدستم برسه، همون لحظه يه حکم مي يرم و ...ميام به آزمايشاهت و
find every last ounce of that super charged grass you're growin' out there.
تا آخرين تيکه ي اون بساط عِلميت رو جمع مي کنم...
I don't care how many money men you're payin' off. You understand?
و برام هم اصلا مهم نيست قدري ول بالاش دادي فهميدي؟
Yessir.
بعله قربان
You ain't foolin' a soul by cleanin' up.
با اين سلموني که رفتي هم هي کسي رو خر نمي کني
I know just what you is.
من ذات کثيفتو بو مي کشم
That ain't at all what I asked you.
اين اون يزي نبود که ازت رسيدم
I asked you why you was supposed to be here three days ago,
رسيدم که را سه روز يش قرار بود اينجا باشي
and you just walk in here now?
و امروز يدات شده؟
We just had some business back at home we had to take care off, is all.
يه مشکلاتي خونه داشتيم که بايد حلشو مي کرديم همين
I heard you made an appearance in Broken Bow.
شنيدم که توي کافه يدات شده بود
Well, I just stopped in at the Me Tote Em, there.
آره فقط يه سري اونجا رفتيم
My girl wanted some licorice.
نامزدم هوس شيرين بيان کرده بود
Everybody knows those Fuller boys work out of the Me Tote Em.
همه مي دونن اون سراي سيريش اونجا کار مي کنند
Even the police know that.
حتي ليس ها هم مي دونند
She wanted the licorice.
نامزدم ويار کرده بود ديه
I sure hope my money's in Yonder Bay.
مطمئنم که اوضاع ولاهايم مرتبه، آره؟
Well, that's just the thing.
آره، ببين موضوع همينه
Either that, or you got samples of what you goin' be up to down there.
شايد هم تو نمونه اي از کارت رو براي من آورده باشي
Don't tell me you done interrupted my day of rest.
نو که بقيه ي روز منو (شنبه ي يهوديان که در آن کاري جز عبادت نمي کنند) مي خواي خراب کني
To other shit, I got no interest makin' its way between my ears.
مي دوني که علاقه اي به شنيدن خبر بد ندارم
We went to the wrong temple at first.
ما اولش کنيسه رو اشتباه رفتيم
- Temple Jester? - Over on Utica.
- کليساي جستر؟ - توي اوتيکا
If I wanted to go to church, I'd be a Krustian.
اه مي خواستم کليسا برم که مسيحي مي شدم
Might make your life a little easier.
فتيم شايد خواسته باشي يکمي راحتتر زندي کني (دين يهود به قوانين سختش معروفه)
Who says my life ain't easy?
کي فته زندي من راحت نيست؟
I don't know. Maybe folks ain't too partial to Jews.
نمي دونم، شايد رفقا با دينت راحت نيستند
Law would never mark out a Jew as a dope dealer, neither.
قانون، يهوديان رو به عنوان دلال مواد مخدر نمي شناسه
They leave me alone, by and large.
س کاري هم به کارم ندارند (تا وقتي زير تر دين يهود باشم)
The way of the world is mysterious,
...رسم دنيا خيلي عجيبه
but every man has his place, each accordin' to his lights.
اما هر کسي نون بازوي خودش رو توش مي خوره
That could be.
خوب فتي
Shaver and Wendell done presented to you a deal, Brady.
شِيور و وَندال (دو تا غولي که شت سرش ايستادند) يشنهادي بهت داده بودند، درسته برادي؟
Uh, opportunity. Now, either you got my money in that bag,
يشنهاد فرصتي رو بهت داده بودند، خب حالا يا تو ول منو توي اون کيف همراهت آوردي
or we gonna talk about expanding your situation down there.
يا ما مي رويم بيرون و قدمي مي زنيم و در مورد توسعه ي کارت در اينجا صحبت مي کنيم (يعني مجبوري زير دست من اينجا کار کني)
Well, I can't do neither.
خب، هي کدومشون
- Why not? - I wanna have a family.
- را نه؟ - مي خوام خانواده تشکيل بدم
I ain't never had a dad myself, so I aim to be a good one.
خودم که در نداشتم، ولي مي خوام در خوبي بشم
So, I'm done. I might be growin' for myself,
س من ديه کارم تمومه و مي خوام براي خودم کِشت بدم
but I ain't gonna be growing for you or nobody no more.
و براي تو يا کس ديه اي کار نکنم
At least, not in the selling facet.
يعني جنبه ي فروشي نداشته باشه
So, that's a bag full of money payin' me back for settin' you up down there.
س ول من بايد اون کيف جلوي اهات باشه
- Well, now, hear me out, Pug. - That's gettin' harder,
- هنوز حرفم تموم نشده - ...س قراره کارمون ره بخوره
because of all the shit I'm listenin' to.
بخاطر حرفايي که دارم ازت مي شنوم
Okay, look. Me and Bolger. We gonna take that whole operation
خب، ببين، من و بالر ...مي خوايم که کل کاري که
that you paid for, we gonna haul it up to Broken Bow.
تو ولش رو دادي، زير دست خودمون باشه... مي خوايم حمل ونقل محصول هم دست خودمون باشه
We gonna set it up, turn it over to the Fuller brothers.
مي خوايم که اسمشو به برادران فالر عوض کنيم
I'm gonna teach them everything I know.
مي خوام يزايي که بلدم رو بهشون ياد بدم
You can take Bobby Fuller and brain, and stick it in the head of a cat,
تو اه مغز داداشت رو برداري و تو سر يه ربه بزاري
that animal will keel over and die.
اون حيوون از روي درخت ميفته و ميميره
- Me and Bolger will do whatever it takes. - Who is paying me back?
- من و بالر همه ي کارا رو مي تونيم خودمون سامون بديم - ول من ي ميشه؟
I'm working on that, but you ain't never said nothing about a timetable.
حواسم بهش هست، اما نمي تونم بهت زمان خاصي رو قول بدم
- Ohhh! It has been over a year, hadn't it? - Yea, so?
- اوووه، تا الان يکسال ذشته، نه؟ - خب که ي؟
In all that time, have you heard me ask you for a nickel?
تو همه ي اين مدت شنيدي که من ازت دوزار ول بخوام؟
In all those 12 months?
توي کل اين 12 ماه؟
No, but you and me both know I've been selling you at a cut rate.
نه ولي جفتمون مي دونستيم که اوضاع تو ه جوريه
Ohhh! So! Now you want me to be nice!
اوووه، حالا مي خواي که بهت لطف کنم
Well, I guess I do. What the fuck is wrong with that?
آره فکر کنم حقمه! مشکلت يه؟
Brady, my people been kicked out of near every country on this planet.
برادي، مردم من تقريبا از هر کشوري که توي اين دنيا بوده بيرون انداخته شدند
My granddaddy came here, because of the pogroms in Russia.
دربزر من از روسيه اومد اينجا ون اون طرف کشت و کشتار بود
He traveled all over the South, selling czachkers out of a wagon,
تمام جنوب رو طي کرد تمام راه بيرون وان رو شيريني فروخت
because nobody else wanted the job
ون کس ديه اي حاضر نبود
of taking a wagon 50 miles a day.
هر روز 50 مايل توي يه وان اين کار رو بکنه
Jews got good with money, because Krustians didn't wanna touch it.
يهودي ها با ول خوب کنار اومدند ون مسيحي ها نمي خواستند دستشون هم بهش بخوره
Now, Krustians say, Jews got all the money.
حالا، مسيحيا مي ويند که ول يش يهودي هاست
I wonder how that happened?
موندم را اينجور شده؟
I give nearly every cent I make to the State of Israel,
من هر ي داشتم رو خرج اسرائيل کردم
because Israel is where we put our foot down, and we said no more.
براي اينکه اونجا جايي بود که تونستيم راحت امون رو توش بذاريم و توضيحي هم نديم
We ain't gonna be took advantage of no more!
!دنبال يز بيشتري هم نيستيم
I would just like a little more fucking time.
بابا من فقط يکمي زمان خواستم
Well, ya know what I'd like?
خب مي دوني من ي مي خوام؟
I'd like everybody in the world to call me a cocksucker and give me a dollar!
من حاضرم هر الاغي توي دنيا بياد به من به احمق و به جاش يه دلار ول بزاره کف دستم
Why is that?
را؟
Because that way I'd be rich and everybody'd love me!
ون ولدار ميشم و همه دوستم دارند
Shaver, check that pickle. And if they ain't got my money, kill those sons-of-bitches!
شِيور اون وامونده رو برد و اه ول من توش نبود جفت اين حرومزاده ها رو بکش
Now, Pug, it ain't gotta go this way.
نه، ا قرار نيست از اين اتفاقا بيفته
Oh, bring it on, sonny.
بيا به جون
You tricked me, motherfucker! I sure as shit gonna bleed.
به من کلک مي زني کله ي وکت رو مي کنم
All right, shit! All right, shit!
خب، خب
Get the spray paint!
اسري نقاشي رو بيار
Because Jesus is a loving and forgiving God,
بخاطر اينکه مسيح بخشنده ست
He don't care where you've been. He don't care whatcha done.
اون به کاري که کردي ناه نمي کنه اون به کاري که مي خواي بکني هم ناه نمي کنه
He just wants to love ya up, and wants you to do the same to him.
اون فقط مي خواد که بهت محبت کنه و تو هم در حقش همين کار رو انجام بدي
Ya know, He was there when you was born,
مي دونين، اون در وقت تولد در کنار شما بوده
and He just wants you back again before you perish.
و مي خواد که قبل از اينکه زنديتون رو نابود کنيد به سمتش بررديد
He loves ya and holds ya and He comforts ya,
اون دوستتون داره، در آغوشتون مي يره و آرامتون مي کنه
and gives ya everlasting rest,
و آرامش ابدي رو بهتون اعطا مي کنه
because Jesus is a compassionate God.
ون مسيح مهربانه
Brings to mind the story of the old man who's walking down the beach,
بخاطر بياوريد داستان مردي که در ساحل قدم مي زد
He stops and he's just... he's just takin' in the glory of the creation.
اون ايستاد و...و به عظمت آفريدار هستي فکر کرد
And, suddenly he realizes there's somebody behind him, and he turns, and he looks,
و به يکباره احساس کرد کسي شتش ايستاده ...س رخيد و با تعجب ديد که
and it's Jesus!
اون مسيحه...
And he says, "Lord, Lord, if..."
...و فرياد زد: خداوندا، خداوندا
Are you listenin' to this bullshit?
تو اين مزخرفات رو وش مي دي؟
Hey, Mom.
سلام مامان
Billy?
بيلي؟
Well, you've got a nice view.
منظره ش که قشنه
I like watching the storms come in.
من وقتي مي بينم طوفان ميشه لذت مي برم
You used to get so scared of 'em.
تو قبلا ازش مي ترسيدي
Do ya still?
الانم مي ترسي؟
I don't think anything like that scares me anymore.
فکر نکنم يزي مثل اون ديه منو بترسونه
If you aren't scared these days, you aren't alive.
خب اه از يزي نترسي ديه زندي نمي کني
I'm sure many people would agree with you.
مطمئنم خيلي ها نظر تو رو دارند
Coming here didn't scare you?
اينجا نترسوندت؟
- Nah, ah, maybe a little. - Why?
- نه، شايد يه ذره - را؟
Ah, I didn't come here to have that conversation, Daisy.
من اينجا نيومدم که باهات بحث کنم، ديزي
So, one minute you were there, and then you were gone. What happened?
س يه دقيقه هستي و بعدش دوباره ميري ي شده؟
No, I'm... I'm serious, I'm really... really not gonna do this.
نه، من...من جدي مي م قرار نيست از اين کارا بکنم
Why, Billy?
را بيلي؟
Billy? Why?
بيلي؟ را؟
All right. Because we needed a mother,
خب، ون ما مادر احتياج داشتيم
and not another friend to get fucked up with.
نه يه رفيقي که ند بزنه
- I could be both. - But you weren't both.
- مي تونستم براتون جفتش باشم - اما نبودي
Are you saying that I didn't raise you?
مي ي که من کمکت نکردم يشرفت کني؟
I don't know what the fuck you were doing.
نمي دونم تو ه غلطي کردي
Reading every book you read, every paper you wrote,
هر کتابي خوندي رو من هم خوندم هر مطلبي نوشتي رو هم خوندم
even when they were beyond me.
حتي اه ازش يزي سر در نمي آوردم
I didn't need you to tell me I was smart,
احتياجي نيست تو به من بي که باهوش بودم
- I needed guidance. - You never needed anything.
- من راهنما مي خواستم - تو هي وقت يزي نمي خواستي
- Brady did! - You don't have to tell me about Brady.
- برادي که مي خواست - نمي خواد اي اون رو وسط بکشي
I... I don't need to be reminded. Don't you think I know that every time he comes here?
من...من احتياجي به يادآوري ندارم فکر مي کني نمي دونم هميشه اونه که مياد به ديدنم
All I ever wanted was a tiny taste of something
تمام يزي که مي خوستم ...احساس يه ذره
resembling a normal and rational life.
زندي درست و حسابي بود...
Where everything's a lie?
ببينم، تمام زنديت دروغ بود؟
Do you know that I actually went away to school
...هي وقت فهميدي که من مدرسه رو ترک کردم
and took a class in the culture of the 60s,
...و کلاسي با حال و هواي دهه ي 60 رو رفتم...
just to try to understand the way you lived?
فقط براي اينکه بفهمم تو ه جوري زندي مي کردي؟...
The... The choices that you made,
...انتخابايي که تو مي کردي
just to... to try to make sense out of all that new freedom,
فقط...فقط براي اينکه از آزادي هايي که مي فتي سر در بيارم
and... and upheaval and fucking anarchy?
و...و انقلاب و اون هرج و مرج لعنتيت؟
Ya know, and the... the problem is you tore everything down,
آره و ميدوني مشکلم اين بود ...که تو همه يز رو خراب کردي
but you were too lazy to actually build anything, as an alternative.
ولي اونقدر تنبل بودي که... نخواستي دوباره بسازيشون
As usual, you've got it all figured out.
مثل هميشه، خودت کل مطلبو رفتي
Am I ever gonna see you again?
مي تونم دوباره ببينمت؟
I don't know. I don't think so.
نمي دونم فکر نکنم
I'm sorry.
متأسفم
Yea, me, too.
منم همين طور
They say everything can be replaced.
They say everything can be replaced.
They say every distance is not near.
They say every distance is not near.
So I remember everything - [indistinct]
So I remember everything - [indistinct]
Of every man who put me here.
Of every man who put me here.
I see my light come shinin'
I see my light come shinin'
From the west unto the east
From the west unto the east
Any day now
Any day now
[indistinct]
[indistinct]
Now you tell Buddy, the next time I slide into Broken Bow,
خب، حالا به بادي مي ي که ...دفعه بعدي که من اينجا اومدم
if Bolger wants to shake a snake, or if I just want a refreshin' potable,
اه بالر خواست بره بشاشه... ...يا من دلم مشروب خواست
I expect a little more fucking time...
...مي خوام که راحت باشم و کسي مزاحمم نشه...
[Screaming on and on and on] They say that every man must fall
[Screaming on and on and on] They say that every man must fall
Yet I swear I see my reflection
Yet I swear I see my reflection
Somewhere so high above this wall
Somewhere so high above this wall
Jack Rothbaum, known as Pug to his friends,
جک راتبام، معروف به ا
was a controversial figure in Tulsa's small Jewish community.
...هره ي جنجالي جامعه ي کوک يهويديان تولسا
An enormous success in the oil bill equipment business,
...به دليل داشتن موفقيت هاي بي شماري در صنعت نفت منطقه...
he gave millions of dollars to the State of Israel,
و اعطاي ميليون ها دلار به اسرائيل
- as well as, other Jewish and statewide causes. - Uh, oh.
- مثل ساير يهوديان متمول منطقه بود - واي
Pug Rothbaum was a man of generosity and valor.
ا راتبام مرد دلير و سخاوتمندي بود
Every nickel he made, most of it went to help others,
هر سکه اي که بدست مي آورد با اميد به اين بود که  بتونه اون رو در راه کمک به ديران خرج کنه
- Jews, Christians, everyone. - He didn't. - What?
- يهودي، مسيحي، هر کسي - اون که اين کار رو نکرده؟ - ي؟
Our community and the city of Tulsa have lost a great man.
جامعه ي ما و تولسا، مرد بزري رو از دست داد
Indeed, Pug Rothbaum's name adorns buildings and signs all over our city and state,
به حق، اسم ا راتبام زيور همه ي ساخته هاي ما در اين ايالت ست
including various hospital wings, his Museum of Indian Heritage,
از جمله بيمارستان شهر موزه ي تاريخ هند
and this rest stop on the Will Rogers Turnpike.
و استرحتاه بين راهي Will Rogers Turnpike
Hey, y'all, we're home! Hey, buddy.
سلام به همي، ما برشتيم طوري بادي؟
- What have you done? - What's it all about? - This?
- ه کردي؟ - ي شده؟ - اين
One curious aspect of this case is that the swastikas were drawn backwards,
موضوع عجيبي که توي اين حادثه ديده ميشه طرح صليب شکسته نازي هاست که روي ديوار محل حادثه نقش بسته
indicating either haste
که نشون ميده کار يا با عجله همراه بوده
or a lack of familiarity with this most infamous of anti-Semitic emblems
و يا قاتل با اين نشانه ي شرم آور ضد يهود آشنايي کامل نداشته (نشانه ي نازي ها رو برعکس کشيده اند)
or, perhaps, rather more implausibly, that Hindus were involved.
و يا به احتمال بسيار نايزي دست هندوها در اين قضيه بوده (بخاطر ماجراي موزه شون)
I ain't no Hindu!
من که هندو نيستم
The guy you owed money to, a Jew up in Tulsa?
کسي که بهش بدهکار بودي يه يهوديه تولسايي بود؟
Don't point your finger at me! I've been with Bolger all day!
با انشتت منو نشون نده من تمام روز با بالر بود
Oh! Come! Ugh! Hey, Billy! Hey!
بيخيال بابا، هي، هي، بيلي
Ah! Calm 'er down now, I don't want to upset Colleen. I mean it.
آروم باش، نمي خوام کالين ناراحت بشه باور کن
- Tell me that you didn't do this. - He was gonna kill us, and I had no choice.
- بهم بو که اين کار تو نيست - اون مي خواست ما رو بکشه، اره اي نداشتيم
Ugh, ugh! You... You... You... You go to the cops and explain things.
...واااااي! تو...تو...تو تو الان مي ري يش ليس و اعتراف مي کني
You go and hide! You do anything but that! And... And... What...
تو مي تونستي بري م و ور بشي !تو هر غلطي مي تونستي بکني بجز اين ...حالا...حالا...حالا...اين
What were those swastikas?
اين صليبا ديه ي بود؟...
Well, those were the symbols that the Nazis put on all their little trinkets.
خب، نازي ها هميشه اينو روي نشان هاشون مي کشيدند
I... I... I'm familiar with the contextual history of the swastika.
من...من...من...خودم با اين تاريخه ي اين علامت آشنا هستم
Why would you want it to look like a hate crime?
را شبيه يه جنايت نژادي کرديش؟
So it don't look like a drug crime!
ون مي خواستم شبيه جنايت دوايي نشه
Great! Perfect! Just... just confirm that we're the
...خوبه! عاليه! فقط ...اين قضايا فقط اينو ثابت ميکنه که
rednecked hick state that everybody thinks we are.
ما واقعا همون دهاتي هاي احمقي هستيم !که همه تصور مي کنند
Don't you talk down on Oklahoma!
حق نداري در مورد اوکلوهاما (منطقه شون) اينجور صحبت کني
How? How is it possible that you are so brilliant,
طوري؟ طوري ميشه تو، همزمان هم اينقدر ...باهوش باشي و
and so monumentally, selfishly ignorant at the same time?
و هم اينقدر کله خر و احمق؟...
Oh, look! When you ever been in a situation you had to fight your way out of?
ببينم، کِي شده جنابعالي توي موقعيتي قرار بيري که مجبور بشي براي زنديت بجني؟
Whether it was you or someone else?
حالا براي خودت يا کس ديه؟
I don't put myself in those kind of situations!
من خودم رو هي وقت داخل اين جور موقعيت ها نمي کنم
Well, that's the real world, Billy. I hate to tell ya,
خب، دنياي واقعي همين طوره !ببخشيد که از خواب خروشي بيدارت مي کنم بيلي جان
and if you had to kill someone to protect you
...و اه مجبور بشي براي دفاع از خودت
or your own, you'd do the same thing I done.
و يا بستانت کسي رو بکشي... دقيقا همون کاري رو مي کني که من کردم
I got a baby coming.
من قراره به دار بشم
I... I... I am leaving tomorrow.
من...من...من فردا از اينجا مي رم
You gonna turn me in?
مي خواي من رو لو بدي؟
No. I don't know. I don't know what I'm going to do!
نه! نمي دونم، نمي دونم ه کار مي خوام بکنم
Listen, listen. This guy. He hauled drugs all over this state.
ببين، ببين! اين بابا، تو تموم ايالت جنس خش مي کرده
- You said he didn't sell. - He sold to the ones what sold 'em.
- تو که مي فتي فروشنده نيست - به فروشنده ها مي فروخته
All right? Now, he will come down here to force me
خب؟ حالا هم اومده بود که منو مجبور کنه
to explain the shit I don't even wanna talk about.
يزايي رو براش بم که نمي خواستم کسي بدونه
They're gonna find you, and you're gonna get killed,
اونا يدات مي کنند و آخرش مي کُشنت
or you're gonna go to jail, and then where are your wife and kid gonna be?
يا مي اندازت زندان اون وقت تکليف زن و به ات ي ميشه؟
That's the beauty of it. Well, I wasn't up there.
قشني نقشه ام همين جاست من که اونجا نبودم
I was down here. Remember?
من اينجا بودم، يادته؟
Ah! You asshole!
به ررو
Do you have any idea what you're doin' to me?
اصلا مي فهمي منو تو ه دردسري انداختي؟
Son of a bitch!
حرومزاده
Billy! Ugh!
!بيلي
- You are going to ruin my life! - Ain't nobody gonna know! Ugh!
- زنديم رو به لجن کشيدي - کسي يزي نمي فهمه بابا
Go answer the phone.
برو تلفن رو جواب بده
- Colleen'll get it! - Just answer the fucking phone!
- کالين جواب ميده - اون وشي لعنتي رو جواب بده
Hello?
الو؟
No, it ain't. It's his brother.
!نه، نيستن من برادرشونم
- Who... Who is it? - Well, he's right here, I know.
- کي...کيه؟ - الان اومدن
Hello?
بله؟
- Bill, ah, Nathan Levy. - Nathan?
- بيل، ناتان لِيوي هستم - ناتان؟
Ah... How did.. How did you get this number?
آه...ه جوري...ه جوري شماره ام رو يدا کردي؟
I hope you don't mind. I, ah, spoke to Maggie Harmon down at Brown.
اميدورام ناراحت نشده باشي من با منشيت در دانشاه براون صحبت کردم
Is this a bad time?
بد موقع زن زدم؟
It's fine. Ah, you know what? Hang on one second.
نه خوبه، ببخشيد يک لحظه وشي خدمتتون
Sorry, Nathan, go ahead.
ببخشيد ناتان بفرمائيد
Well, you didn't hear this from me, Bill. But you're about to be ambushed down there.
اينو از من نشنيده بير بيل اما اينجا دارند در موردت تحقيقاتي مي کنند
- By whom? - Something about a coed and a poem,
- براي ه؟ - ...براي بعضي اشعار و آماردادن هاي رمزي
and some other behavior, which I would rather allow you to infer.
و بعضي رفتارهايي که ازت زارش شده که خودت بهتر مي دوني
What? You've got to be kidding me. Nobody would say that.
ي؟ شوخي مي کني اين وصله ها به من نمي سبه
Apparently there was a witness, Bill.
ظاهرا شاهدي هم داشتي
Nathan... Nate... Nathan, listen to me.
ناتان...نات...ناتان، وش بده
- That is absurd. - That's why I'm reaching out.
- اين مضحکه - براي همينه که باهات تماس رفتم
But until whatever happened blows over, we can't...
...اما تا وقتي شايعات تموم بشه، ما نمي تونيم
I understand.
مي فهمم
- Everything all right? - No, it isn't.
- همه يز مرتبه؟ - نخير نيست
Now, where can I find the signal for this?
کجا آنتن يدا ميشه؟
I wrote a poem for you in Latin for when you got back.
من براي وقتِ برشتنت يه شعر به زبون لاتين نوشته بودم
It was incentive of Virgil in dactylic hexameter,
تو مايه هاي ليلي و مجنون بود
and it was all about what would happen if we were together in the [indistinct].
و يزايي رو که اه با هم بوديم، انجام مي داديم توش نوشته بودم
Stop. Inappropriate. I don't wanna hear it.
حرف بي جايي بود نمي خوام ديه ادامه بدي
So, I was in the library, and Mark Laub read it over my shoulder.
من توي کتابخونه نشسته بودم و مارک لوب شت سرم وايستاده بود و همه ي نوشته هام رو خوند
He site-translated it? Oh, no, he was really good.
همون جا تونست ترجمه ش کنه؟ نه، اون خيلي کارش درسته
He had like five hortatory subjunctives.
ظاهرا قبلا با اين مدل اشعار سروکار داشته
Anne, didn't you tell him that it was just a fucking poem, that it never happened?
آني، تو هم بهش نفتي که اينا فقط شعر بوده و حقيقت نداشته؟
Yes, but he didn't believe me, so he went to the Department.
فتم، اما باورش نشد و صاف رفت آموزش
I guess he was really pissed about some B+ you gave him on a Lucretius paper last year.
فکر کنم سر نمره ي کمي که ارسال بهش داده بودي، شاکي بود
Fucking hell!
ندت بزنه
- Did you give him a B+? - I don't remember, Anne.
- داده بودي؟ B+ بهش - يادم نمياد که
So, that bitch, Maggie Harmon, said she caught us that day
و اون زنيکه، مي هارمون ...که اون روز يرمون انداخت هم
- making out with my shirt off in your office. - Ohhh!
- لباس منو توي اتاقت يدا کرده بود... - واااااي
So, I went to her, and I told her the truth, and I begged her.
من هم رفتم براش توضيح دادم ...و بهش التماس کردم
But the door was closed, and I was partially undressed.
...ولي خب روز ماجرا در بسته بود و منم نيمه لخت بودم
And then Professor Lockwood said that,
...و بعدش رفسور لاکوود فت...
in a world of phenomena, appearances are truth.
!در دنياي ديده ها، ظواهر همان حقايق هستند
Going around quoting the cynics. He's such a fucking lightweight!
رفت و همه جا حرفام رو جار زد خيلي کثافته
- I don't.. I don't wanna hear any more. - Bill! When are you coming home?
- ديه...ديه نمي خوام يزي بشنوم - بيل، کي بر مي ردي؟
Stop it! I told you to leave Stacy alone!
صبر کن بهت فتم اِستيسي رو به حال خودش بذار
She's been on my nerves since Hebrew school.
از زماني که مدرسه ي هِربو مي رفتم اون روي اعصابم بود
- Eat shit, Gabe! - Well, after you eat mine!
- زر نزن ِيب - خفه بمير
Don't you dare speak to anyone that way, Stacy Feinman!
نبينم ديه با کسي اينجور صحبت کني اِستيسي فايمن
He cusses all the time! And so do you!
اون هميشه فحش ميده خودتم همين طور
You both make spectacles of yourselves back there!
حسابي خودتون رو امشب نشون داديد
The pizza there sucks compared to the pizza in New York!
يتزاي اينجا هم جلوي يتزاي نيويورک بايد بوق بزنه
Well, it is the pizza that we have!
خب، اين تنها يتزاي اينجا هست
And, by the way, did I hear you ask your mother for money?
و در ضمن، درست شنيدم که شما از مادرتون ول خواستين؟
Honey, I don't wanna talk about it.
عزيزم بي خيال
- Don't you have any pride? - Of course, I do.
- تو  اصلا غرور سرت ميشه؟ - معلومه
- It's your mother! - We're strangling, Suzie. Strangling!
- اين مادرت بود - ما وضعمون داغونه، سوزي، مي فهمي؟ داغون
The credit card bills alone.
فقط در مورد قبض هاي کارت اعتباريمون بود
- Now, until I get my practice up... - When? When? - I told you. I told you.
- ...حالا تا زماني که من دوره ي آموزشيم رو تموم کنم - کي؟ کي؟ - بهت مي م، بهت مي م
It's when the kids make friends at school, and we meet the parents.
وقتي که به هام توي مدرسه رفيق يدا کنند و ما خونواده هاشون رو ملاقات کنيم
I hate the kids at school! They suck! They're a bunch of idiots!
!از به هاي مدرسه متنفرم! دهاتين !يه دسته احمقند
A brutal murder occurred earlier today, after Mr. Rothbaum attended Sabbath services.
قتل وحشيانه اي که امروز براي آقاي راتبام بعد از برشتن از مراسم مذهبيشون اتفاق افتاد
- I said, when? - Yea, Dad? - Shh! Everyone be quiet!
- فتم کي؟ - آره بابا؟ - همه ساکت بشن
Sources close to the investigation say it was a hate crime.
منابع آاه اطلاع دادند که اين يک حرکت نژادرستانه بوده
Mr. Rothbaum was last seen alive at approximately 1:00 pm
آقاي راتبام آخرين بار ساعت 1 بعد از ظهر زنده ديده شده بودند
by fellow worshippers in Congregation Nevei Kodesh, here in Tulsa.
در جمع دعاکنندان در کنيسه ي تولسا
I'm supposed to get three kids out of the car by myself?
ببينم من تنهايي بايد اين سه تا به رو از ماشين ياده کنم؟
Just give me a minute!
يه دقيقه صبر کن
Bill Kincaid
بيل کين کِيد
Honey! I'm just gonna, ah... Don't wait up for me!
...عزيزم، من ميرم جايي منتظر من بيدار نمون
What?
ي؟
Well, 180 dollars will limit ya, but it don't mean you can't put a bullet
خب، 180 دلار کارت رو يک کمي سخت ميکنه ...ولي حداقل به يک لوله ميرسه که بذاري توش
in there that's gonna pack a wallop.
و مانع رو به روت رو بترکونه...
I... I really don't need... need the bullets.
من...من حقيقتش به لوله ها احتياجي ندارم
None of my business, friend, but you carry a firearm, you'd better be ready to use it.
به من ربطي نداره رفيق، ولي وقتي داري اسلحه ي رم حمل مي کني، بهتره براي شليک هم آماده باشي
Uh, huh. Well, ah, see, it's... it's really more for protection.
درسته ولي...بيشتر براي حفاظت از خودمه
Now, these here is hollow points.
اينايي که اينجان رو جرقه هاي الهي صدا ميکنيم
I... I appreciate that, but, um, like I said, I... I'm content...
من...من ممنونم ازتون ولي ...همونطوري که عرض کردم به همين قانعم
Dog eat dog. You wanna be the one who's chowin' down.
س، س رو مي خوره مي خواي خورده بشي؟
I really don't... I don't plan to chow down.
نه... نه برنامه اي براي خورده شدن ندارم
I'll just take the gun.
فقط تفن رو مي برم
Yup, nope. Well, that's what... honey, you just got to trust me on this.
...آره، نه. خب براي همينه که من به من اعتماد کن عزيزم
Yes, right.
آره، درسته
Tomorrow night at the latest.
نهايتا فرداشب
Just give 'em... Give everyone a big kiss.
فقط همه رو...همه رو از طرف من ببوس
And I'm telling you, you was at that rest home, plain as day.
بهت ميم که ما توي خونه ي سالمندان بوديم
And Erica. Looked like a choirboy.
و اون هم اونجا بود
So, how could he have been there, here, and in Tulsa?
حالا ه جوري ميشه که اون هم اونجا بوده هم اينجا، و هم تولسا؟
He was in Tulsa before he was here.
قبل از اينکه اينجا بياد، تولسا بوده
This is one big waste of my time.
دارم وقتمو اينجا تلف مي کنم
And I tell you what else! I'd better not hear about any vigilante bullshit.
دارم بهتون هشدار مي دم بهتره که از اين اراجيف ديه نشنوم
And you know why he would've been in Tulsa?
و مي دوني را اون توي تولسا بوده؟
No, Buddy, educate me!
!نه بادي جان، روشنم کن
Because him and Pug Rothbaum was fixin' to make a lot more than grass down here.
ون اون و ا برنامه داشتن حشيش بيشتري از اون يزي که اينور توليد مي کردند اونجا کشت بدهند
- Who told you that? - Pug Rothbaum
- کي بهت فته؟ - ا راتبام
He was gonna push me and Jimmy out of Broken Bow.
مي خواست من و جيمي رو از  اينجا بيرون بندازه
He was into Pug for more than $200,000 for the equipment in his grow house.
اون بالاي 200 هزار وق به ا بابت دم و دستاه کشت علفش بدهکار بود
You tellin' me the truth, Buddy?
راستشو به من مي ي ديه، بادي؟
Ya know, there's... there's rumored to be
...مي دوني که اينجا شايعات
excellent noodling in the rivers around Boston.
از باد سريعتر مي يه...
How about that.
طور؟
Okay
خب
Hey
آهاي
You ain't gonna stop off and see mom one more time?
نمي خواي بري و مامان رو يکبار ديه ببيني؟
I don't think so.
نه
Well, I'll see ya when I see ya.
باشه، بعدا مي بينمت
Hello, there.
سلام
You have got to be kidding me.
شانسو ببين
- You know this guy? - Sort of.
- مي شناسيش؟ - يه مقدار
- Well, I'll be damned. - How can we help ya?
- واي سر - ه کمکي مي تونيم بهتون بکنيم؟
Okay, ah, which of you was it I met on the airplane?
خب، کدومتون رو من توي فروداه ديدم؟
You! And you murdered Pug Rothbaum!
!تو! س تو ا راتبام رو کشتي
- Get in the house! Get in the house! - No! Don't go there! Don't go there!
- برين داخل، برين داخل - نه! نرين، نرين
- Over there! - Just calm down! Just calm down!
- اونور - آروم باش، آروم باش
Calm down! It's all right!
آروم باش، خيلي خب
No, no, you get back... Get back... No, no...
...نه، نه، برو عقب ...دستتو بکش،نه،نه
No, no, no... Back! Back!
نه، نه، نه...عقب برين
- I got hollow points! - Hollow points?
- من جرقه ي الهي دارم - جرقه ي الهي؟
Join it! Join over! Get in the cluster! Get in the cluster!
!جمع شين! جمع شين
No, this is not happening. I've got a plane to catch.
نه از اين خبرا نيست من بايد به هوايمايم برسم
Well, I'm afraid I can't let you do that.
فکر کنم نشه که برسي
You are not pointing that gun at me.
سر اون اسلحه رو بير اون طرف
- Join the group! - This is not happening!
- برو يش اونا - نخير
- Billy, Billy, come on.
- بيلي، بيلي، بيا
Thank you!
مرسي
Now, lis..., now, listen. Wha... Wha... Wha...
وش کن
Why don't you stop waving that thing around?
ميشه اون تفن رو هي تکون تکون ندي؟
I don't wanna hurt anyone.
نمي خوام به کسي صدمه اي بزنم
No, all right. Then let's... let's just put the gun down, then.
خب، س اسلحه رو غلاف کن
I just wanna talk.
بابا جون مي خوام فقط صحبت کنم
- Why are you doing this? - You flew down here to be his alibi.
- س را اينجوري مي کني؟ - تو اينجا رواز کردي که براي اين بهونه بشي
Making him a murderer, and you an accessory, and this is a Christian state.
اينو قاتل کني، خودتم شريکش بشي !موقعيت کاملا مسيح وار شده
We're very Old Testament, when it comes to murder.
وقتي اي قتل به ميون مياد ما يهوديا يشکسوت ميشيم
He'll get the chair, and you'll get life!
اون به ول مي رسه تو به زندي جديد
Who the fuck is this guy?
اين ديه ه کوفتيه؟
You're an orthodontist.
تو که اورتودنتيست هستي
I am drowning in debt! I've been trying to set up a new practice,
!من بدهکار هم هستم ...دارم دوره ي آموزشيم رو تموم مي کنم
but I still owe on the insurance premiums from the last one!
اما هنوز حق بيمه رو بدهکارم...
Plus all the equipment! I have a wife and three kids!
به اضافه ي ول تمام تجهيزاتم رو در ضمن زن و سه تا به هم دارم
Why don't you get to the fucking point?
را اينقدر حاشيه مي ري؟
Until my kids can make friends at school, and we meet their parents!
تا وقتي که به هام توي مدرسه دوست يدا نکنند و ما با خانواده هاشون آشنا نشيم
No, no, no, listen. Bill, Bill, hey, Bill!
!نه، نه، نه، بيل، بيل،آهاي بيل
- I am a guy that you met on an airplane! - Keep back! Keep back! I said keep back!
- من کسي هستم که توي فروداه ديدي - !عقب وايسا! عقب وايسا! بهت مي م عقب وايسا
- Really, really, please. - I really mean it.
- جداً، جداً، خواهش مي کنم - جدي مي م
Get the hell back!
م شو عقب
Pull the trigger. Put a bullet in my skull. I give up. It's perfect.
ماشه رو بکش يه لوله توي مغزم شليک کن من تسليمم
I'm sorry! I'm sorry!
!ببخشيد، ببخشيد
It's fine. Just go home.
!!!اشکالي نداره، برو خونه
- Billy, we can't let him go now. - We are.
- بيلي، نمي تونيم بزاريم اين بابا بره -  را مي تونيم
Just let it go, and everybody just go home.
بذاريد بره، و بعدش همه مي تونند برردند خونه
Go, go.
برو، برو
-Brady! Brady! - Hey, hey, you!
- برادي، برادي - هي تو، تو
Where do ya think you're going?
کجا داري ميري؟
- Get back! - Aaahhh!
- وايسا عقب - آآآآه
- Bill, no!
- بيل، نهههههه - آآآه ه ه ه
Brady!
برادي
Janet, call 911!
ژانت زن بزن اورژانس
Baby, I think my mama might have called it.
عزيزم، فکر کنم مامانم اينو قبلا يش بيني کرده بود
She might have been right!
حق داشته
Police coming.
ليس تو راهه
Bill. Hey, Bill!
بيل، هي، بيل
We're gonna need an EMT.
ما اورژانس احتياج داريم
- Bill... Hey, Bill! - Bill... Bill... Bill...
- بيل...هي بيل - بيل...بيل...بيل
Gimme that! Gimme it.
اونو بده به من، اونو بده
Look at me... at me...
منو ببين..ناهم کن
Go see that rabbi up in Tulsa.
برو و خاخام رو در تولسا ببين
All those drawings we did at Pug's. Tell her we didn't mean nothing by 'em.
جريان ما و ا رو بهش بو بو که منظوري نداشتيم
Just promise me. You promise me?
قول بده، قول مي دي؟
You're gonna tell her yourself.
خودت خوب مي شي و  شخصا بهش مي ي
Okay. Now you ain't killed nobody.
خب، جريان اينه که تو کسي رو نکشتي
Diogenes Laertius has recorded for us the Greek philosopher, Epicurus's
ديوجانس براي ما از فيلسوف يوناني ايکور نقل مي کنه (نام فيلسوف يونانى که معتقد بود خوش ذرانى منتهاى سعادت، و خوبى است)
thoughts on death.
در رساله ي در مسير مر
It is irrational to fear an event,
...ترس از حادثه بي معني مي باشد
if when that event occurs, we are not in existence.
ار هنامي که اتفاق مي افتد... ما لطمه اي نديده باشم
And, since when death is, we are not, and when we are, death is not,
و وقتي نوبت مردن شد، آماده نباشيم... ...و وقتي آماده بوديم، وقت مردن نباشد
then it's irrational to fear death.
س ترس از مر هم بي معناست...
One might just as well, Epicurus argued,
...مورد ديري که ايکور به اون استدلال مي کنه
fear birth.
ترس از تولده...
I was born just a few minutes before my brother, Brady.
من ند دقيقه زودتر از برادرم، برادي، به دنيا اومدم
He lived life on his own terms, indifferent to fear,
اون با فلسفه ي خودش زندي کرد بي تفاوت نسبت به ترس
either his own, or those of others.
بي تفاوت نسبت به ترس خودش، يا ترس هاي ديران
And, let's be honest.
و بذاريد روراست باشم
By any normal measure, my brother was a criminal and a colossal fuckup.
با هر نوع مقياس امروي جامعه ما ...برادر من فردي مجرم و داغون محسوب مي شد
But, in the years that we were together,
...ولي در طول سالياني که با هم بوديم...
when we were growing up,
...و با هم بزر شديم...
he gave me the happiest, freest times
...اون به من شادترين لحظه هايي که...
that I will ever know.
در زنديم داشتم رو بخشيد...
I don't know why it took me so long to realize that.
نمي دونم ه يزي مانع فهميدن اين نکته در طول اين سالها بود
I left Little Dixie because of my own fears.
...من شهرم رو بخاطر ترس هايم ترک کردم
My greatest regret is that
...بزرترين افسوس من در زنديم اينه که
I never told him how difficult that really was.
هي وقت نتونستم بهش بم که قدر برايم سخت بود...
Bolger, how'd you get those scars?
بالر، اين زخم ها سر ي نصيبت شده؟
- Prison, with your brother. - My brother wasn't in prison.
- زندان، با داداشت - داداش من هي وقت زندان نرفته
Two years on possession. I think he ain't wanted you to know that.
دو سال سر ماليات رفته بود احتمالا نمي خواسته تو بدوني
Saved my life, too.
زندي منو هم نجات داده بود
Three guys jumped me with box cutters. Your brother, Brady, went berserk.
سه تا هيکل با کاتر (نوعي تيغ) روي سرم ريده بودند ...داداشت، برادي هم از کوره در رفت
Kept the both of us alive in there.
جفتمون رو زنده از اون قضيه بيرون کشيد...
Can't believe he never...
...باورم نميشه که اون هيوقت
Wished I could've repaid the favor.
دوست داشتم يه روزي براش جبران کنم
So tell my baby I said so long
So tell my baby I said so long
Tell my mother I did no wrong
Tell my mother I did no wrong
Tell my brother to watch his own
Tell my brother to watch his own
Tell my friends to mourn me none
Tell my friends to mourn me none
I'm chained upon the face of time
I'm chained upon the face of time
Feelin' full of foolish rhyme
Feelin' full of foolish rhyme
There ain't no dark till something shines
There ain't no dark till something shines
I'm bound to leave this dark behind
I'm bound to leave this dark behind
So, to what do I owe this visit?
خب، من ه کاري کردم که اين لطف نصيبم شد؟
My brother killed Pug Rothbaum.
برادرم، ا راتبام رو کشت
Your brother?
برادر تو؟
Who's the... same man who was shot by Ken Feinman.
هموني که...هموني که توسط کِن فِينمن کشته شد
Have you told the police?
به ليس هم فتي؟
I will.
مي م
He wanted you to know that it wasn't a hate crime.
مي خواست که شما بدونيد که اين يک قتل نژادرستانه نبوده
I find it hard to believe your brother didn't have something against Jews.
براي من باورش سخته که برادر تو هي دشمني با دين يهود نداشته
I know, but he didn't.
مي دونم، اما اين حقيقته
Then I'll have to believe you.
س بايد حرفتو باور کنم
Is there something else?
مطلب ديه اي هم مونده؟
Why... Why do you think...
...را...را شما تصور مي کنين که
Why do we...
...را ما بايد
We are animals, Professor Kincaid.
ما جزء حيوانات هستيم، رفسور کين کِيد
Brains that trick us into thinking we aren't.
مغزمون ما رو با افکاري فريب مي ده که براي خودمون نيست
What do I... What can I do with that?
يکار مي تونم...يکار مي تونم با اين مشکل بکنم؟
- Repair. - What?
- بايد اصلاح بشي - ي؟
All of us. You, me,
...همه مون، تو، من
your brother, Pug...
برادرت، ا...
We break the world.
ما دنيا رو به هم ريختيم
Help repair it.
بايد توي اصلاحش به هم کمک کنيم
Hey, come on over here.
آهاي، بياين اينجا
- What's this about, Bolger? - I'll let Billy speak.
- موضوع يه بالر؟ - بهتره بيلي صحبت کنه
Have a seat.
بشينين
Well, go on. Say whatcha got to say.
حرف بزن، ببينيم ي مي خواي بي
- My brother had a lot of equipment. - His grow house. - Yea
- برادرم کلي ابزار داشت - لخونه ش - درسته
We talked to a lawyer. The police can't confiscate it.
ما با يه وکيل صحبت کرديم ليس نمي تونه اونا رو ضبط کنه
Now, it's a high quality system. It's hydroponic.
تجهيزات يشرفته اي هستند هستند hydroponic
I'm proposing to sell it to you.
مي خوام که به تو بفروشمشون
That's the whole list.
اين هم ليستشونه
That's at a... a discount price.
قيمتش هم با تخفيفه
Yea, well, I don't see it quite like this.
آره، اما من مطلبو جور ديه اي مي بينم
Why not?
را؟
Because your brother never paid Pug for that equipment.
ون برادرت بابت اين وسايل ولي به ا نداد
- So what? - So why I gotta pay you for it?
- خب که ي؟ - خب را حالا من بايد به تو بابت اينا ول بدم؟
Because my brother is dead. I have to cover funeral costs.
ون برادرم مرده و من بايد خرج کفن و دفنش رو بدم
He had bills that weren't paid.
اون کلي قبض رداخت نشده داره
He had a mortgage, and his wife is expecting a baby now.
اون خونه ش رو رهن ذاشته بوده همسرش هم حامله ست
Okay, all I'm trying to do is to cover his debts
مي بيني، تمام جوني که دارم مي کنم ...براي اينه که قرض هاش رو بدم
and leave his family with a little something.
و آخرش براي خونواده ش هم يه يزي بمونه...
- Can you understand that? - Well, I'm one of his debts, see.
- مي فهمي؟ - خب، من هم يکي از طلبکاراش بودم
Ya know, before your brother and Bolger got out of the penitentiary,
ميدونستي، قبل از اينکه داداشت و بالر از ندامتاه ...بيرون بيايند
I had this whole area, southeastern Oklahoma.
تمام اين منطقه زيردست من بود... ...تمام جنوب اوکلوهاما
And Pug Rothbaum come to me for his grass!
و ا هم براي علفش يش من ميومد...
And now you're going to have all of that again and better product besides.
و حالا هم جنابعالي همه منطقه رو با محصول با کيفيت تري زيردستت داري
Your brother owes me that equipment!
برادرت ول اين تجهيزات رو به من بدهکاره
Come on, man! Don't you want to repair the world?
بيخيال بابا نمي خواي به اين دنيا يه کمکي بکني؟
- What? - We're breaking the world! Don't you want to fucking repair it?
- ي؟ - ما دنيا رو با اين کارامون به هم ريختيم نمي خواي توي اصلاحش کمکي کني؟
What I want is for you to give me that equipment and then to go back East
يزي که مي خوام اينه که اين وسايل دستم برسه ...و تو هم برردي به شرق
with all the other faggots who think that New York City is the only place on Earth.
با تموم احمقايي که فکر مي کنند... نيويورک تنها جاي باحال روي زمينه
- I don't live in New York. - Well, that don't mean that
- من که توي نيويورک نيستم - کلا فتم
you don't think you're better than us! Now, do it.
يعني تو فکر نمي کني از ما بهتري؟ نه؟ را جونم دقيقا همين فکر رو مي کني
You know what? We are better than you! We use our powers of thought!
مي دوني يه؟ معلومه ما بهتر از تو هستيم ما از فکرمون استفاده مي کنيم
- Don't you turn your back on me! - Fucking hick!
- شتت رو به من نکن - دهاتي احمق
- Don't you walk away! - Just keep walking. Don't look back.
- راه نيفت همين جوري برو - ادامه بده، برنرد
Motherfucker.
مادرقحبه
Help! Help me!
!کمک! کمکم کن
- I can't. - Get it out!
- نمي تونم - بکشش بيرون
It's a bow. I think got a fletchette.
با کمون زده فکر کنم سر يکانش رو احساس مي کنم
Oh, my God! No, no, no!
!خداي من، نه! نه
He's been shot! Fuckin' arrow!
!تير خورده، يه يکان بي صاحاب رفته تو بدنش
Folks, wanna come with me.
رفقا، با من بياين
Now, the arrow missed his heart by an inch
...خب، يکان با اختلاف کمي از کنار قلب
and his spine by centimeters.
و فقراتش ذشته...
So, what does this mean for him?
خب، اوضاعش ه جوريه؟
Well, it'll be a long recovery.
خب، زمان مي بره تا خوب بشه
I guess I don't need to tell ya this, but you saved his life.
فکر کنم احتياجي نباشه بم اما زنديش رو مديون تو شده
[Baby crying] Yes, yes, yes, dear...
...بعله، بعله، بعله عزيزم
Billy, it's fixin' to rain.
بيلي، مي خواد بارون بيره
Thanks, mom.
مرسي مامان
Think I'm just gonna sit here for awhile.
دلم مي خواد يک کمي اينجا بشينم
In the rain?
زير بارون؟
I used to be so scared of these summer storms.
من قبلا از طوفان تابستون ها مي ترسيدم
And when I went East, I missed them.
و از وقتي رفتم شرق دلم براشون تن شده
I was so frightened, I used to hide in the closet and cover my ears.
اونقدر مي ترسوندم که مي دويدم توي کمد لباسا ...و وشهام رو محکم مي رفتم
And I hated that.
و از اين کار متنفر بودم...
So, I went to the library, and I studied them.
...س رفتم کتابخونه و در مورد طوفان ها خوندم
Learned everything I could about them. How they happened. What made them happen.
و هر يزي که مي شد رو در موردشون ياد رفتم... ...که ه جوري تشکيل مي شوند، ي باعثشون ميشه
The name of every cloud.
اسم تمام ابرها رو ياد رفتم...
And?
و؟
They still happened.
هنوز مي ترسم
Mind if I stay out here with you?
اشکالي نداره من هم همين جا بمونم؟
I wish you would.
دوست داشتم اينو بي
Lonely are the free
تهيه و تنظيم: احسان قريب Sonick74ir2000@yahoo.com :.:.:www.9Movie.ir:.:.: